<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Satana noēmata, or, The wiles of Satan in a discourse upon 2 Cor. 2. 11 / by William Spurstow ...</title>
            <author>Spurstowe, William, 1605?-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 212 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61206</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5096</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22598</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12442843</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12442843</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62133</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61206)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62133)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 948:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Satana noēmata, or, The wiles of Satan in a discourse upon 2 Cor. 2. 11 / by William Spurstow ...</title>
                  <author>Spurstowe, William, 1605?-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 110 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, II, 11 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Devil --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Temptation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62133:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62133:1"/>
            <p>ΣΑΤΑΝΑ ΝΟΗΜΑΤΑ: OR, The Wiles OF SATAN IN A DISCOURSE Upon 2 <hi>Cor. 2. 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>William Spurſtow</hi> D. D. Late Miniſter at <hi>Hackney.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Be ſober, be vigilant; becauſe your Adverſary the Devil, as a roaring Lion, walketh about ſeeking whom he may devour. Whom reſist ſtedfaſt in the faith,</q>
            <bibl>1 Pet. 5. 8, 9.</bibl>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1666.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:62133:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62133:2"/>
            <head>The Wiles of Satan.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2 Cor. 2. 11.</bibl>
               <q>Leaſt Satan ſhould get an advantage of us: for we are not ignorant of his devices.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Chapter I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Containing an Introduction to the words, and diviſion of them.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eldom or never do Judges become Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates; they give Sentence on the <hi>Crime,</hi> but they never plead the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of the Offender. In doing the one, they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the moſt ſolemn duty of their place: But in undertaking the other, they deſcend as it were from the <hi>Throne</hi> to the <hi>Bar.</hi> and go both below themſelves, and beſides the Rule: A pleading Judge being no well-tuned <hi>Cymbal.</hi> And yet if we look
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62133:3"/> into theſe two Epiſtles of <hi>Paul,</hi> we ſhall find him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing both theſe diſtinct <hi>Offices</hi> towards the ſame <hi>Perſon</hi> in one and the ſame <hi>Cauſe.</hi> In the firſt we may behold him as a juſt, and ſevere <hi>Judge,</hi> drawing forth the ſpiritual Sword of the Church, and ſmiting with it the Inceſtuous perſon, in as great an height of zeal as <hi>Samuel</hi> did <hi>Agag,</hi> to the cutting of him off from all Communion with that body, of which he was a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. He being the firſt (as <hi>Calvin</hi> expreſſeth it) <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitorens Eccleſiae tam turpi not â maculaſſet.</hi> who ſtained the beauty of that Church with ſo foul a Sin and Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall. And if we turn our eyes again to this Second Epiſtle and Chap<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, we may ſee the ſame Apoſtle performing the Office of a moſt Compiſſionate <hi>Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate,</hi> in pleading the Cauſe of him to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> who by his Command was cut off, and caſt out from among them. He who was the ſubject of his Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as a <hi>Judge,</hi> is now the object of his entreaties as an <hi>Advocate.</hi> And the Arguments which he uſeth for his reception into the boſome of their love are not more numerous than weighty. A brief view of ſome of which will not be impertinent, in regard they lead us in an orderly way unto the <hi>Text,</hi> which is the laſt, but not the leaſt of thoſe many perſwaſive Pleas which he urgeth on his behalf.</p>
               <p>The firſt is drawn from the Law of Equity, which is, as <hi>Philo</hi> calls it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Nurſe of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. <hi>Sufficient to ſuch a man is the puniſhments which was inflicted of many,</hi> Ver. 6. Rewards and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, though they be the golden hinges, upon which the vvelfare of every ſtate turns, yet are they to be regulated by a juſt, and ſi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> meaſure. No Cenſures are to be exceſſive, much leſs Church Cenſures, vvhoſe end is chiefly medicinal, they being (as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62133:3"/> the Corrections of God) <hi>Caſtigationes Emendatoriae, non interfectoriae;</hi> Chaſtiſements to procure amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not to work ruine.</p>
               <p>A ſecond Plea is from the preſent danger, <hi>Leaſt perhaps ſuch an one ſhould be ſwallowed up with overmuch ſorrow,</hi> Verſ. 7.</p>
               <p>Inward troubles and perplexities of mind are far more corroſive and waſting then outward: The <hi>Wheeles</hi> of a Clock, whoſe motion is ſtrong, wears ſooner then the <hi>Finger</hi> which moves gently without. They are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes like a tempeſtuous and angry Sea, which doth not onely toſs the Ship but ſink it. And it became not them to be Spectators of any Mans ruine, without caſting forth ſome Cord or Plank, by the help of which he might reach the Shore. It is <hi>Jobs</hi> Cenſure of him <hi>who ſheweth not pitty to the afflicted, that he hath forſaken the fear of the Almighty,</hi> Job 6. 14.</p>
               <p>A third is, <hi>That he might have a Proof of them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be obedient in all things,</hi> Verſ. 9. Spiritual Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as well as Natural delight in the reiterated acts of their Childrens Obedience, as being the moſt legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Characters of a Son-like Diſpoſition: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle, who had onely a ſingle triall of their willing complyance to his commands, ſeekes the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of it by a ſecond Teſtimony: that as they had ſhewed themſelves forward in putting away from among them that Perſon, whoſe ſin was not to be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralelled among the Heathen; ſo now they would, at his entreaties, ſhew the like readineſs in the readmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of him into their love and favour who of a preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Sinner, was become an humble and broken Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiary.</p>
               <p>A fourth Plea is from his own practiſe; <hi>He had for their ſales forgiven him, as in the ſight</hi> or Perſon <hi>of</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62133:4"/> 
                  <hi>Chriſt,</hi> verſ. 10. That is, as he firſt awakened them to judge the ſin, with which for a time they were not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected; ſo now, by his example, in his ſincere Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning of it, as in Chriſts ſight, he did induce them to do the like, and alſo teach them how to temper their zeale aright, in being neither too remiſs in uſing the Cenſures of the Church, nor yet too rigorous in retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them when inflicted: both extreames being alike prejudicial to the beauty of their zeale. It being with it, as with the Blood in the Body, which if it be <hi>dilutus,</hi> watrie, through phlegme; or <hi>ſublimatus nimis,</hi> too fiery through Choller, makes the Complexion too <hi>wan</hi> and ſallow, or too <hi>red</hi> and high coloured.</p>
               <p>A fifth Plea is that that comes under preſent Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and is to be inſiſted on as the Subject of this preſent Diſcourſe: <hi>Leſt Satan ſhould get an advantage of us,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In this Verſe there are two principal parts, which do equally divide and ſhare it between them.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>A uſefull Caution</hi> of Circumſpection; <hi>Leſt Satan ſhould get an advantage:</hi> The general Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of which is implyed in the relative Particle <hi>Us.</hi> For in this matter, Satan, as a Common Adverſary, did endeavour more then a ſingle Supplantation; he did not <hi>Bait</hi> a <hi>Hook,</hi> but <hi>Spread</hi> a <hi>Net.</hi> For ſhould the Inceſtuous Perſon through deſpair miſcarry, it might occaſion a Rent between the <hi>Apostle</hi> and the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that would hardly be made up: It might render the Goſpel leſs amiable to thoſe upon whom it had newly dawned; and cauſe it to be as unwelcome and offenſive, as light is to weak and ſore eyes. It might blemiſh the Cenſures of the Church, as having too deep a Tincture of Phariſaicall Rigor: and having their whole Power tending rather to deſtruction then to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62133:4"/> Therefore it is that the Apoſtle, like a wiſe Phyſitian, is more then ordinary anxious, that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient die not under their hands, and Satan get the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of them both by his ſin, and ſorrow. In the Original it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which by Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters is diverſly expounded. The <hi>Vulgar</hi> reades it, <hi>Ne Circumveniamur:</hi> That we be not Circumvented by Satan, who like a cunning Wreſtler, or Fencer, is various, and uncertain in his Motions, that he may take the better hold, or ſtrike his Adverſary with the greater advantage. <hi>Beza, Ne ſuperemur;</hi> That Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan get not by far the better of us: not by open Force, but by unfore-ſeen artifices, and ſlights. <hi>Eraſmus, Ne occupemur à Satanâ:</hi> Leſt Satan ſhould uſurp upon us; that is, leſt he who hath nothing of right, ſhould by fraud obtain a kind of poſſeſſion among us, by ſnatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and taking him from us as his own, who is a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of our body; the entire union of which we ought to preſerve from ſuch Ruptures and Avulſions, by the due tempering of our <hi>zeale</hi> and <hi>charity</hi> towards thoſe, who by the ſtrength of Temptation fall into ſin, and by their deep ſorrow teſtifie their unfeigned Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for ſin. Others again (Etymologically enough) conceive it to be a <hi>Metaphor</hi> taken from Avaritious and greedy Perſons, that for Gaines-ſake do in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts and Bargaines, by guile and fraud over-reach thoſe whom they deale with. In all theſe Expoſitions there is ſo full a Concurrence and agreement to the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Place, and the Practiſes of Satan; as that I ſhall not, by giving a preheminence unto any one above the other, determine the Judgment of the intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Reader which to take, but wholly leave him to his free Choice. This onely I ſhall intimate, that our Tranſlation ſeemes <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o favour the laſt.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:62133:5"/>
               <p>The ſecond is <hi>the forcible and prevailing Motive</hi> to ſtir up their Circumſpection: <hi>For we are not ignorant of his devices.</hi> The Greek word for <hi>deviſes,</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: which in its general acceptation doth ſignifie the thoughts, and muſings of the minde (as <hi>Eſtius</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) but in a more ſtrict and confined ſenſe it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed unto ſuch thoughts that are on purpoſe framed to deceive; and by ſtudied artifices to bring about deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ends in any kind whatſoever: Such are <hi>Ambuſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> in War, <hi>Slights</hi> in Wreſtling, <hi>Deceits</hi> in Gaming, <hi>Pollicies</hi> in State, <hi>Fallacies</hi> in Diſputing, Dark and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered <hi>Sentences</hi> in Rhetorick, in which one thing is ſpoken and another intended: theſe <hi>Quintilian</hi> in his <hi>Inſtitutions</hi> calls <hi>Noemata.</hi> When therefore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, that <hi>he was not ignorant of Satans Cogitations</hi> (as the <hi>Vulgar</hi> and others alſo render the words) it is not to be underſtood of any intuitive power and ability which he aſſumed to himſelf, of diſcerning and prying into the moſt retired thoughts of the Prince of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which are onely open and naked to the eye of God, whoſe Sacred Royalty it is to ſearch the hearts both of Men and Angells; but of a practical and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimental knowledge, which he, and other Belivers alſo attain unto, by a diligent obſervance of their wayes and actions, in which they diſcover the miſterious arts and ſnares of the Tempter, ſpread like the Nets of a cunning Fowler, to intrap them in every motion and ſtep that they make, not onely by his various allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments unto ſin, but alſo by his perverting of their beſt Duties, ſo as to make them to be loſers thereby, and himſelf to be the onely gainer. And this was it in which he ſought to get the better of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> turning their juſt zeale againſt the ſin of the inceſtuous Perſon, into an inexorable ſeverity againſt his Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62133:5"/> though he was well nigh ſwallowed up of Sorrow.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Containing the main Propoſition, and Summ of the Diſcourſe.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I May haply be deemed to have lingered over-long upon the borders of the Text, and to have ſpun out the Explication of a few words into too long a Thread; but my purpoſe herein was onely to free them from any difficulty which might ſeem to ſit upon them, as <hi>dark ſhadowes on the tops of the Mountaines,</hi> or <hi>Miſts on the Valleys, that intercept the light.</hi> And now methinks they are like a bright and unſpotted Mirrour, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly preſents the Object, or <hi>Species</hi> that is ſhed upon it, to the eye of every beholder; So clearly do they hold forth <hi>this one Propoſition,</hi> in which both the parts of the Verſe, the <hi>Caution</hi> of Circumſpection given, and the <hi>Ground,</hi> or Motive to it, do equally center.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That Satan is full of deviſes, and ſtudies arts of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvention, by which he unweariedly ſeekes the irrecovera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ruine of the Soules of Men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is the obſervation of the learned <hi>Zanchy,</hi> that <hi>Satan</hi> hath above twenty diſtinct Names and Appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions given unto him in the Scripture; ſome of which ſet forth <hi>the high impurity</hi> of his nature, in oppoſition to that ſtate of <hi>holineſs</hi> in which the bleſſed Angels ſtand, and from which he is fallen; and in this reſpect he is ſtiled an Unclean Spirit, <hi>Mark</hi> 9. 25. A Spirit of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62133:6"/> Wickedneſs in the abſtract, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 12. The Evil One, by way of eminency, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 19. Other of his Titles ſpeak the <hi>Soveraignty and Dominion</hi> which he exerciſeth over multitudes of Men, and hence he is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by our Saviour, the Prince of this World, <hi>John</hi> 12. 31. And by the Apoſtle, the God of this World, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 4. Some again of them point out <hi>his Malice,</hi> and fierce <hi>rage,</hi> armed with Power, hence he is called the Accuſer of the Brethren, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 10. A roaring Lion, not ſeeking whom he may bite, but whom he may devour, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 8. A great red Dragon, that out of his mouth ſends forth Waters, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 15. and with his Tail eaſts down the third part of the Stars of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 4. Others of them again declare <hi>his craft to deceive,</hi> his <hi>wiles</hi> to enſnare, his dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity and skill to tempt: and in this regard he is ſaid to be the Father of Lies, <hi>John</hi> 8. 47. The Old Serpent, that by his windings and turnings deceives all the World, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 9. The Tempter, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. 3. And this Name ſome think to be ſo peculiar to the Devil, as that it agrees to no Perſon, or thing beſides, ſave as it is his Inſtrument; that though Men tempt <hi>Inſtrumental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> the World <hi>Materially,</hi> yet <hi>Efficiently</hi> Satan onely is ſaid to Tempt. But amongſt the many wayes by which the Holy Writ doth ſignalize the tranſcendent emnity that the Devil beareth to the Church and Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen of God, there are none that are to be more eyed, or dreaded then his pernicious wiles and devices. He <hi>captivates</hi> more by his bidden <hi>Snares,</hi> then he <hi>woundes</hi> by his fiery <hi>Darts:</hi> He poiſons more as a hiſſing <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> then he devours as a roaring <hi>Lyon:</hi> He cheates more as a <hi>Tempter,</hi> then he hurts as an <hi>Accuſer.</hi> And as he in his immediate workings hath alwayes been, and ſtill is more miſchievous to the Church and Truth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62133:6"/> of God, by his Machinations and arts, then by his open force: ſo likewiſe have thoſe Inſtruments, and Emiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of his in the ſucceſſion of all Ages, proved more fatall to the welfare of Religion, that have uſed rather the <hi>Head</hi> of this <hi>Serpent,</hi> then the <hi>Paw</hi> of this <hi>Lyon;</hi> and have carried on their deſigns rather by fraud and ſubtilty, than by an hoſtile War and defiance. The <hi>Midianites</hi> vexed <hi>Iſrael</hi> more by their Wiles, <hi>Numb.</hi> 25. 18. then the combined Powers of all the Kings of <hi>Canaan</hi> by frequent Battells. The <hi>Samaritan</hi> Faction obſtruct the building of the Temple by falſe inſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, <hi>Ezra</hi> 4. 6. By ſcornfull de<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſions, <hi>Neh.</hi> 4. 3. By pretenced compliances of building with <hi>Zerubba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> and the chief of the Fathers, <hi>Ezra</hi> 4. 2. So <hi>Julian</hi> the infamous Apoſtate did more indanger the Goſpel, and leſſen the number of its Profeſſors, by his Serpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Pollices, then all his Predeceſſors had done by their bloody Perſecutions, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> and other of the Ancients have truly obſerved. Yea, and Romiſh <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> it ſelf, though it hath exceeded in cruelty all the <hi>Edomites</hi> of the former Ages, in making her Garments red, and her ſelf drunk with the blood of the Saints as with new Wine, yet the advancement of the Papacy hath been effected, after the Working of Satan, with all power, and ſignes, and lying wonders; and with all deceivableneſs of unright couſneſs, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 9, 10. In faining Apparitions of Angels and Spirits, in forging of Decrees of Counſells, and corrupting of Fathers, in ſembling and diſſembling of Piety, in ſwearing and forſwearing, in ſawnings, flatterings, bribings, and the uſe of all arts of couſenage and impoſture that wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it ſelf can deviſe or exerciſe. If then it be a ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y and labour not unuſuall to the Military Profeſſion, to record the Stratagems of the moſt renowned Chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62133:7"/> in War, as <hi>Vegetius, Frontinus,</hi> and others have done; to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the ordering of Armies, and the ranging of them into ſeveral formes, and figures, as <hi>Aelian</hi> in his <hi>Tacticks</hi> hath done; or to Write with <hi>Lypſiois</hi> of the Warlike Engines and Weapons of the Ancients: It cannot but be both gratefull and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to acquaint ſuch who are engaged in a ſpiritual Warfare againſt Satan and his infernal Legions, what be his methods of Temptation, his arts of looſe skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhing, and cloſe fighting with thoſe againſt whom he ſets the Battel in array: What be the wayes of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treates, and fained flying, that ſo they may neither be enſnared by his Wiles, nor vanquiſhed by his Power. To this end therefore, in the purſuance of that needfull Truth which I have propounded to inſiſt on, I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the performance of theſe five following Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> To demonſtrate the great abilities of Satan, as a Tempter, to effect and bring about his curſed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, in making his Suggeſtions to become our Sins; his Snares our Chaines; his Baits our Food; his Will our Rule; and his Inventions our Circumventions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> To ſet down, not by way of Enumerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but of Inſtance, ſome of thoſe grand Stratagems, and uſuall Polices, which too often render him the Conquerour, and us the Captives: For he who hath (as <hi>Jerom</hi> ſpeakes) <hi>nomina mille,</hi> a multitude of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Names, hath alſo <hi>mide nocendi artes,</hi> as many arts to hurt and deſtroy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To furniſh the Combatans in this War and Conflicts, with Weapons out of the Tower of <hi>David, Cant.</hi> 4. 4. the Armory of the Holy Scripture, ſuch, which being mighty through God, may bot<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pierce the Scales of this Helliſh <hi>Leviathan,</hi> though
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62133:7"/> ſhut up together as with a cloſe Seal, <hi>Job</hi> 41. 15. and may alſo ſafeguard them againſt the ſore danger of his poyſonful and fiery arrows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> To reſolve ſome Queries, the diſcuſſion of which will properly fall under the ſubject in hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> To ſhut up the whole Diſcourſe with ſuch practical deductions, and inferences, as may be like the emanations of the Sun, that carry both light and heat with them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein is ſhewed the great ability of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan to tempt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>TO evince firſt the great ability of Satan to tempt, who ever ſince he left his own ſtation, hath never ceaſed to malign ours, and is become both by office and practiſe a Tempter, that he might draw man from his happineſs into the ſame irreparable and curſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition with himſelf, I ſhall offer theſe ſix Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, In his nature he is both a <hi>Spiritual</hi> and an <hi>Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual</hi> Eſſence, in each of which reſpects his advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage over man is very great, who in the moſt refined, and ſupream part of his beeing falls as far ſhort of an Angel, as a ſmall glittering <hi>ſparke</hi> doth of a fair and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62133:8"/> well polliſhed <hi>Diamond,</hi> or a <hi>twinkling ſtar,</hi> of a <hi>reful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Sun.</hi> An Angel (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine in his heavenly Scale</hi>) is a moſt perfect and ſpiritual ſubſtance. But the Soul is a Spirit imperfectly, and by halves; as being the form of an earthly body, and part of a man, who is a middle kind of Creature, and hath ſomething in common with Angels above him, and with Beaſts which are below him. As a Spirit therefore Satan can convey himſelf and his ſuggeſtions both to the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and Will, in a more intimate and efficacious manner than any humane Agent poſſibly can. For when one man becomes a Tempter to another, he uſeth the mediation of the outward Senſes, to which he can only apply and communicate the object; but he cannot by any Phyſical or natural power gain an immediate acceſs unto the internal faculties of the ſoul, and lodge the temptation, as <hi>Joſephs</hi> Steward did the Cup, in <hi>Benjamins</hi> Sack without his privity. But ſuch is the power of this infernal Angel, as that though he be totally debarred from all kind of intercourſe with the immediate and immanent operations of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſoul, and can no more look into the thoughts, and muſings of the heart, than a common eye can pry into the bowels of the earth, and deſcribe thoſe nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conceptions with which it travels in its womb; yet he can as eaſily get into the Fancy, which is next to that myſterious Chamber of the Soul, which to God alone is all light, and to every created power all dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as any man can enter into a room, that is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of a Key that gives him free admittance. And he can make uſe of all thoſe <hi>Species</hi> and Signatures of things that are lodged in it, diſpoſing and ordering them as a Painter doth his many Colours, that lye confuſedly before him in their ſeveral She<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, to expreſs
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62133:8"/> the Portraiture and Image of that Perſon, which he would delineate by them: And he can both continue and reiterate the preſentation of the objects which he offers to the fancy, as oft and as long as it pleaſeth him. Now, how much ſuch a power, when permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God, can further a complyance in the ſoul to all thoſe ſuggeſtions which the Father of lies doth ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtill, we may eaſily conjecture, if we d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> but a little conſider, what the natural uſe of the Fancy is both to the Underſtanding, and the Will. To the <hi>Underſtanding</hi> it is a prompt aſſiſtant in matter of inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſupply it with variety of objects whereon to work; and from the quickneſs of its operation, the <hi>multiplicity, levity,</hi> and <hi>volubility</hi> of the thoughts do chiefly ariſe, which when they become exceſſive through an undue, and over-haſty obtruſion of the <hi>Species,</hi> are to be deemed both in natural and moral things as a diſeaſe, and diſtemper of the Faculty, rather than a power or perfection; in regard that the worth of ſome objects doth juſtly require an immoration and fixed ſtay of the thoughts upon them. To the <hi>Will</hi> its office is to elicit and excite its deſires towards ſome conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and pleaſing object, in which for the moſt part it is ſo ſucceſsful, as that oft times plauſible Fancies do more take and ſway with the Will, than knotty and ſevere Arguments; there being a natural aptneſs in men to be moved by ſuch inducements, as carry in them more beauty to <hi>entice,</hi> than force of reaſon to <hi>compel;</hi> the freedom of the Will being ſeemingly leſs infringed in the one than in the other. When there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Satan, by reaſon of the ſpiritualneſs of his being, can have ſuch a free acceſs unto the Fancy, and can improve all the images and repreſentations of things that are in it, to the inſinuating of himſelf,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62133:9"/> and his Serpentine ſuggeſtions both to the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Will, and that ſo <hi>inwardly,</hi> as that he is ſaid to <hi>put it into</hi> the heart of <hi>Judas</hi> to betray Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13. 2. To fill the heart of <hi>Ananias</hi> to <hi>lye to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt,</hi> Acts 5. 3. So <hi>powerfully,</hi> as that the Scripture uſeth the ſame word to expreſs the working of Satan in the Children of diſobedience, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 3. by which it ſets fo<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h the efficacious, and powerful working of God in Believers, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 13. How can it otherwiſe be but that he muſt needs be a powerful, and prevailing adverſary? But yet this difference muſt be put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the operations of the one and the other, that the Spirit of God works by <hi>divine infuſions</hi> of grace, which effectually ſway the ſoul to an aſſent or conſent, Satan only by <hi>moral perſwaſions,</hi> which may be power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to ſollicite, but not to conſtrain. And in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect he is (as <hi>Hierom</hi> truly ſtiles him) <hi>Hoſt is infirmus, qui non poteſt vincere niſi volentem,</hi> A feeble and weak enemy, who can only overcome him that yields, not him that reſiſts; and hurts him that puts his weapons into his hand, not him that keeps them in his own.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, As he is a <hi>Spiritual,</hi> ſo he is alſo an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual</hi> being; and by the ſame Law of Creation, by which he excells man in the one, he far alſo outſtrips him in the other. Now, if in the underſtanding of <hi>Adam</hi> there was ſuch an inbred force and power, that when God brought all the Creatures to him as their Lord, to ſee what he would name them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 19. the did in their name characterize the nature, and not give it unto them at random, (as the <hi>Socinians</hi> wickedly imagine, who make him little above the ſtature of a Child in Knowledge.) How much more muſt the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical nature be endowed with innate, and implanted
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62133:9"/> Species of things, that are more univerſal and exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive unto ſeveral objects, it being the moſt ſupream in the Hierarchy of intelligent Creatures, for whoſe ſake all natural objects were made that they might be known and diſcerned by them. True it is, that Satan by his voluntary defection from God hath loſt that glorious Robe of holineſs that made him a Peer of heaven, and dignified him with the title of a Son of God; and hath alſo (as I conceive) impaired his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural abilities, ſo as that he is become in power, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and knowledge inferiour to thoſe glorious Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Sacred Pallace, who have kept their firſt eſtate, and not departed from that purity that is as ancient as their being. For why ſhould not the ſin of Angels operate as ſtrongly upon them, as the lapſe and diſobedience of man did upon him, whoſe Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals were thereby wholly deſtroyed, and his Naturals ſorely maimed. But though his Fall hath debaſed his being, yet it hath not totally changed it, he hath ſtill the nature though not the perfection of an Angel, and though he be inferiour to them, whoſe equal originally he was in all kind of endowmen<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, yet ſtill he retains ſo great a ſuperiority over the Elementary, Senſitive, and Intellectual part of the world, as that he is not only dreaded for his power, which ſometimes he puts forth in wonderful effects; but is alſo adored for his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and knowledge as a God, by many Nations in it. And it is obſervable, that <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> who 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 1. 2. is called the God of <hi>Ekron,</hi> in <hi>Luk.</hi> 11. 15. is termed the Prince of Devils. In the Kingdom of ſin and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he is a God, but in the Kingdom of grace he is a Devil, and more gaſtly than hell it ſelf by his ſinful deformity; and though he ſeldom of never appears in that dreſs, but palliates and gilds his ſuggeſtions, as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62133:10"/> that they ſometime ſeem to be rather illapſes from heaven than ſmoake ariſing from the bottomleſs pit, and to ſavour more of Angelical purity than of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical filthineſs; yet is he not therefore to be the leſs obſerved by us, but it ſtands us in hand to be the more watchful that have ſuch a Serpent to deal with, that can hide his deadly poyſon with a beautifull and ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning s<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in. And if the Ancient Church, while <hi>Auſtin</hi> was a <hi>Manichee,</hi> and a buſie wrangler againſt them, were wont to pray, (as <hi>Poſſevine</hi> in his life reports) <hi>Ab Augustini Logicâ libera nos Domine,</hi> Lord deliver us from <hi>Auguſtines</hi> ſubtilty and reaſonings; How much more have Believers need to make the like prayer, and often to reiterate it, Lord deliver us from the Arts and Fallacies of Satan, whoſe malice is great, whoſe abilities are matchleſs, and do tranſcend the line of humane wiſdom, when drawn out to the utmoſt period of its extenſion.</p>
                  <p>But beſides, as the meaſure of his knowledge is more full and ample, ſo the manner of his knowledge and apprehending objects is more noble and perfect than the way by which man comes to the knowledge of things that are before him. The Schools, which abound with many intemperate Nicities, and curious Diſputes about the underſtanding of Angels; (in which they juſtly incur the increpation of the Apoſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 18. of intruding into thoſe things which they have not ſeen,) though in other particulars they are not a little divided, yet in this Poſition their Conſent is well in the general, that Angels are <hi>Creaturae intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, ſed non ratiocinantes:</hi> Beeings that are full of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but not ſuch as exerciſe a plurality of intellecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in reaſoning and Argumentation as we do, whoſe knowledge is much built upon Deductions, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62133:10"/> that are derived from confeſſed principles. They grant Angels knowledge not to be <hi>ſimultaneous,</hi> but <hi>ſucceſſive;</hi> ſo as that they know <hi>hoc poſt hoc,</hi> one object after another; but it hath not any <hi>dependency,</hi> ſo as to know <hi>hoc ex hoc,</hi> one thing by or from another, but by one ſingle view or intuition, they fully diſcern the object that is before them; as a man doth the face of a friend as ſoon as he beholds him, without the leaſt heſſitancy, or enquiry who he is. Now if we ſhould take it for granted that the knowledge of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels is thus exact, and that at firſt ſight the ſame object is better underſtood by them, than it can be by the many and moſt pregnant conceptions of the humane intellect, it muſt needs evince the abilities of Satan in tempting to be ſuch, as that man cannot but be as unmeet an adverſary to enter into the Liſts with him, or to maintain a diſpute againſt him, as the young In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant would have been to have reſiſted the Sword which <hi>Solomon</hi> called for, to divide it between the two Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s. But I ſhall not need to wind up the knowledge of Angels to ſo high a key of perfection, or to abet the common opinion of the School, to make it any part of the Baſis or proof in demonſtrating the power of the Devil as a Tempter. For I conceive with <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meron</hi> and others, that their knowledge is <hi>arguitive,</hi> (as he terms it) and not <hi>intuitive,</hi> and that they do reaſon from the effect to the cauſe, from the ſign to the event, as is apparent in thoſe Conjectures that they make about the thoughts of men, which no Angel either good or bad can otherwiſe diſcover, than by ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion which they cauſe externally in the body, or internally in the Paſſions; Only ſuch is the marvelous quickneſs and agility of their Conceptions, as that their intellectual motions are in reſpect of ours as the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62133:11"/> motion of the Sun in the heavens, to the motion of the ſhadow on the Diall; like the ſwift flight of an <hi>Eagle</hi> to the creeping of a <hi>Snail;</hi> or the readineſs of an expert <hi>Arithmetician,</hi> to a ſlow and unskilful <hi>Accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant,</hi> who can in a fewer minutes reſolve that which you demand of him, than the other can in many hours, or happily daies. And this vaſt imparity which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Angelical and Humane underſtanding is enough to make good this firſt demonſtration of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans ability to tempt, as he is both a ſpiritual and intellectuall Eſſence. I ſhall now proceed to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>THe ſecond Demonſtration which aptly confirms the ſame truth with the former is from the durati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and long experience of the Devil, who is thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>skilful to deſtroy,</hi> and to have his temptations like the Arrows <hi>of a mighty expert man, none of which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn in vain,</hi> Jer. 50. 9. In Scripture as he is for his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural endowments, often ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a knowing or intelligent one, ſo he is for his acquired ſubtilty called an old Serpent, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 9. having been well nigh as long a Tempter, nay, a murderer, as he hath been an Angel. Who muſt needs therefore by the many revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, and ſucceſſive generations of men, in which he hath not been an idle ſpectator, but a buſie actor, be more verſed in this Art and Myſtery of wickedneſs, than he was in the non-age and infancy of his being, when he firſt cloathed himſelf in the ſhape of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. For it is proper only to God, to whoſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge all things are preſent, at all times, and before all times, not to be taught by experience. But there is no Creature ſo perfect in its knowledge, but it may
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62133:11"/> and doth learn ſomething for the time preſent, and to come, by the times which are paſt. Experience is li<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e the honey that <hi>Jonathan</hi> taſted, which enlightened his eyes, and made him more fit for action, than he was before: It begets an aptitude for the managing of ſuch affairs, which youth can no more undergo, than <hi>David</hi> could the Armour of <hi>Saul</hi> which he had not tried. Who is more meet to miniſter Phyſick to a weak and crazy patient, than an ancient and well practiſed Phyſician? Who more able to medicine a wounded Spirit, and to eaſe a troubled Conſcience, than an holy and experienced Divine? Who may be better truſted to fit at the Helm of a State than ſuch perſons whom years have made both venerable and prudent? It was the raſh advice of <hi>Rehoboams</hi> young Counſellours, that had well nigh loſt him his Crown, and occaſioned the ten Tribes to fall off from the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> and to form themſelves into a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Kingdom, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12. 20. They ſeemed in their Counſels to exerciſe more mettal and courage than the old men that ſtood before <hi>Solomon</hi> his Father, but the other diſcovered more wiſdom. New Liquor when firſt tunned works and ſtirs more in the Cask, than other; but yet is as unfit to be drawn as their Counſel was to be followed. It was alſo the unmeet choice of perſons in the Council of <hi>Arimine,</hi> deputed by the Orthodox unto the Emperour, that did (as <hi>Sulpitius</hi> judiciouſly obſerves) much injure the truth, they ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing young men that were, <hi>Parum docti, &amp; parum cauti,</hi> little learned, and as little cautious in the weighty Affairs of Religion, with which they were entruſted; when the <hi>Arrians</hi> ſent an equal number of their facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who were, <hi>Senes callidi, &amp; ingenio valentes,</hi> Aged men and crafty, well furniſhed with wit and learning,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62133:12"/> whereby they eaſily prevailed againſt them. And what other iſſue could be expected when unskilful No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices were to take up the Waſters againſt ancient and cunning Maſters of the fence? It is <hi>multitude of years that teacheth wiſdom</hi> (ſaith <hi>Elihu,</hi>) Job 32. 7. and produceth thoſe mature fruits, which youth, that is like a Plant not well rooted, is unable to bear. <hi>Homer,</hi> who extolls his <hi>Neſtor</hi> as an Oracle for wiſdom, as a Fountain for fluency and ſweetneſs of ſpeech, doth yet withall make him as wonderfull for his age, as peerleſs for his perfection. <hi>Joſephus</hi> alſo attributes the Art of <hi>Astronomy</hi> to the Patriarches of the firſt Age, who taught their Poſterity the motions of the Heavens, and the courſes of the Stars, by certain Monuments and Pillars in which they had ſet down the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which themſelves had experienced in thoſe many <hi>Centuries</hi> of years to which the life of man was then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. It being one end (as ſome have deemed) of Gods giving unto them ſo long a time above others, that they might be the Authors of this Science unto after Ages, which otherwiſe after that great <hi>Syſtole</hi> or contraction of mans life by God himſelf, would hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if at all, have been attained to. If then time and experience be ſo requiſite to knowledge and wiſdom, as that it is in ſome things the genuine Parent of it, and in other things the great improver of it; How much then muſt five thouſand years experience enable Satan to tempt, who hath all his time been as diligent an obſerver of men, as he hath been an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary againſt them? How skilful muſt he be in this his black and accurſed Art, who hath compiled his temptations into Syſtemes, which he hath in readineſs by him, and doth with much Art continually make uſe of; being one that knows not in the leaſt what it is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62133:12"/> either to forget, or grow old. Sublunary beings, though they do from time receive a maturity and perfection, yet it is not extended in a Parallel line with their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; as they have a time of beauty and ſtrength, ſo alſo have they an age of deformity and weakneſs; and by their long fitting under the deathful ſhades of the wings of time, are at laſt waſted and worne out. But Satan feeles none of its powerfull impreſſions; time hath rather ſtill added to him, then taken ought from him, multiplying continually thoſe experiences which increaſe his ſubtilty, and advantage him in tempting, as I ſhall ſhew in three Particulars.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> His long experience, as a Tempter, hath made him exact in deſcerning, and chooſing the fitteſt ſeaſons for it, the right timing of which hath a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and effective influence into all kind of Enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes whatever. Upon whoſe Sword doth victory moſt conſtantly build its Triumph, then his, who is moſt diligent in eſpying, or improving of advantages againſt his enemy? whoſe intreaties and perſwaſions do with ſweetneſs more allure, and with mildneſs overcome the harſhneſs and ſeverity of ſome Mens temper, then his, who obſerves <hi>molliſsima fandi tempora,</hi> the ſofteſt and moſt calme ſeaſons of ſpeech? Whoſe Husbandry is crowned with a more ſucceſsfull harveſt than his, who is moſt prudent, and circumſpect about the Seed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time? Opportunity is the joynt of time, and he who wiſely can hit it, is never diſappointed in his aimes. One blow on the Iron as it comes glowing and ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from the Forge, doth more eaſily bow it, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion it, then many re-doubled ſtroakes, when it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to its natural coldneſs. One timely pull doth more facilitate the raiſing of the Bell, then many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull and laborious tuggings at the Rope. Now, as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62133:13"/> there are none equally watchfull to Satan to eſpy any advantages; ſo there are none alike knowing to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcern the very nick of time when the Temptation will be moſt prevalent. Man often miſcarries, and his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings become like Immature Births, becauſe he knowes not his time, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9. 11. But Satan is more ſucceſsfull in his, becauſe he acts from experience, and fully underſtands when and how to apply himſelf, to every age and conſtitution. All his methods of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations are like to the <hi>Aphoriſmes</hi> of Phyſitians, which are nothing but the Collections of experimental ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, drawn into rules, to direct and order their practiſe by. And as <hi>Galen</hi> makes the two Legs, upon which the whole Body of <hi>Phyſick</hi> doth ſtand, to be <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and <hi>experience:</hi> ſo may I ſay, that the two chief parts in which the art of the Devils ſubtilty in tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing doth conſiſt, are the greatneſs of his natural <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> and the length of his <hi>experience.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> His Experience, which now amounts to above five thouſand yeares, doth much advantage him in Tempting, as it makes him dexterous, and ready in the obviating of difficulties, and replying to every doubt that is made, when any ſuggeſtion is propounded and urged by him. For though Satan can with great artifice palliate and diſguiſe the deformity of ſin, by giving it a falſe complexion, by drawing a veil over it, or by ſhewing it halfe-fac'd; as <hi>Apelles</hi> painted King <hi>Antigonus</hi> to conceale the want of his eye: Yet there are but few temptations to ſcandalous and groſs ſins, but at firſt propounding they ſtartle the Conſciences of natural Men, much more of others, and raiſe a cloud of objections, which muſt be ſcattered, before their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent can be gained. Now the objections, or doubts which ariſe in Mens mindes of this preſent Age, are
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62133:13"/> no other then what Satan hath again and again met with in every Generation and Succeſſion of Men; yea almoſt in every Perſon, when tempted by him to the ſame or like ſin. And as he ſtill expect; for the future to find the ſame reaſonings, to hinder and keep off a compliance with his ſuggeſtions; ſo what replies or anſwers he hath experienced to be moſt prevalent, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for perverting the knowledge, or ſtaggering the faith of the tempted, them he ſtill makes uſe of from time to time, to remove the ſame prejudices that ſtir in others, when ſet upon by him, to commit the ſame ſin. And this it is which oftentimes ſtartleth and perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth many Chriſtians, not onely that they are tempted to ſin, but that their pleas and arguments againſt it are ſo ſuddenly anſwered, and replyed unto: No ſooner can they <hi>Ob.</hi> but the old Serpent will <hi>Sol;</hi> and like a ſubtil ſophiſter have alwayes ſomewhat to return to whatever they can Object. But if they did conſider that as the evils to which they are tempted are no other then what hath been ſuggeſted unto thouſands, ſo their arguments brought againſt them are no other, then what he hath been thouſands of times acquainted with, and replyed unto, they would not ſo much wonder at his nimbleneſs in this kind, nor take the way of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as moſt convenient to Oppoſe him. Chriſts incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation <hi>Avoid Satan, Matth.</hi> 4. 10. did more foil him then all Reaſonings and Authorities produced: And the ſafeſt way for us to come off clear with him, is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be reſolute in a flat denial, then buſie in an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger diſpute. When <hi>Naomi</hi> ſaw that <hi>Ruth</hi> was ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly minded to go with her, the left ſpeaking unto her, <hi>Ruth</hi> 1. 18.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> His experience anim<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tes him with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to aſſault the beſt and holieſt of Saints, if not to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62133:14"/> extinguiſh their <hi>light,</hi> yet to eclipſe their <hi>luſtre,</hi> if not to cauſe a <hi>ſhipwrack,</hi> yet to raiſe a <hi>ſtorme,</hi> if not to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their happy <hi>end,</hi> yet to moleſt them in their <hi>way.</hi> Such practiſes he hath found not onely to have ſome ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs againſt the ſtrong, but to intimidate and diſcourage the weak, who are apt from the particular foiles of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Chriſtians in the Faith, to make ſad concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt themſelves, and to cry out, <hi>Quid facient tabulae, ſi gemant columnae?</hi> What ſhall the ſpars and rafters do, if the pillars of the building tremble? What ſhall the reedes and willowes do, if the cedars be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken? Who is he that hath wraſtled with him, and not halted? Who is he that hath entred the Field againſt him, and not been wounded by him? Was not <hi>Noah</hi> a juſt Man, and perfect, one that walked with God, when all fleſh had corrupted their way, ſmitten with the darts of this <hi>Apollyon</hi> between the joynts and the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſe? Was not <hi>Lot,</hi> whoſe righteous ſoul was vexed from day to day with the unlawful deeds of <hi>Sodom,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticed by his arts into the complicated luſts of drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and inceſt? Was not <hi>David,</hi> (a Man after Gods own heart) a ſad inſtance, both of his power and Mans frailty? when through his inſtigation be makes a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond crime to be the vizard of a former; and to cover the deformity of his Adultery, firſt becomes a <hi>Tempter</hi> to ſend <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> drunk to his Bed; and then a <hi>Murderer</hi> when that will not do, to diſpatch him to his Grave? How then ſhall I, who fall as far ſhort of them as a win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters day doth of a Summers day, who have neither that life, heate, or heavenly influences, with which they were filled, be ever able to ſtand? But yet, as no Man ought to preſume that there are any degrees of Grace, that will exempt him from Satans on-ſets, who is not afraid to war with <hi>Michael</hi> and his Angels, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 7.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62133:14"/> much leſs with the Woman and her Seed; ſo none ought to deſpair, by reaſon of the weakneſs of his Grace, of maintaining a Conflict with him, becauſe though his rage hath been great, and his ſtratagems many, yet hath he never been able to make the Seed of Grace, in its conception, to prove abortive; nor to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy a Believer in his <hi>ſwadling-bands,</hi> much leſs in his <hi>Armour.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>A Third Demonſtration, which may farther evince the abilities of Satan in Tempting, is, that it is the onely deſign and buſineſs that he hath propounded unto himſelf, and hath proſecuted with moſt unwearied dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, ever ſince he hath become of an holy Angel an impure Devil.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>First,</hi> It is the grand and ſole buſineſs in which he layes out himſelf, and thereby becomes not onely more dexrerous in it, but alſo more formidable. It is an <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> Proverb, <hi>Liberamea ab homine unius negotii:</hi> Lord deliver me from a Man who hath but one buſineſs to do; he will be ſure to minde and tend it, and thereby get many advantages againſt an incumbred adverſary, who can never obtain the leaſt againſt him. For it is with the powers and faculties of rational beings, as it is with other things, which become more or leſs active, and vigorous, according to the combination or diviſion which they undergoe: Many ſmall wax lights, which of themſelves burn faintly, when put into one Totch or Taper, ſend forth a bright and ſhining flame: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny little Bells which tinkle together to the pleaſing of Children, when melted, and caſt into one great Bell, do affect the ear with a more ſolemne and awfull
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62133:15"/> ſound: and many ſingle Threads, which ſnap aſunder with the leaſt touch, when twiſted together make a ſtrong Cable, which can withſtand the fury and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of a ſtorm. So it is with the Mind, the more it is ſcattered and divided through multiplicity of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, the more weak it is; and the more it is fixed on one ſingle Object, the more maſculine and ſtrong are the operations of it, either in good or in evil. And therefore <hi>David,</hi> who deſires to excell in holineſs, makes it his Prayer, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 86. 11. that <hi>God would unite his heart to fear his Name: Hierome</hi> reads it, <hi>Unicum fac cor meum;</hi> Make my heart one: that is, incline it onely to thy fear; implying thereby, that divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts in the heart do both diſtract and weaken it: When the Scripture likewiſe would ſet forth the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull depravation of Mans eſtate, it ſaith, <hi>That every Imagination of his heart was onely evill continually, Gen.</hi> 6. 5. There is not the leaſt contrary Principle to check, or to reſtrain thoſe ebullitions of luſt, which ſlow and aſcend from the heart, as water from a Fountain, and ſparkes from a Furnace. Now thus it is with Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, he is wholly bent to evil, and makes it his onely ſtudy to dive and ſearch into Men, that he may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter faſten his temptations upon them. It is the queſtion which God puts to him, <hi>Job 1. 8. Hast thou conſidered my ſervant Job?</hi> or as the <hi>Septuagint</hi> renders it, <hi>Haſt thou attended with thy Minde?</hi> In which is implyed what his practiſe and end is, in going too and fro in the earth; he doth not travel it as a <hi>Pilgrim,</hi> but as a <hi>Spy,</hi> that obſerves narrowly every perſon and thing as he paſſeth along: He ſets not forward a ſtep but he doth as it were debate every Mans eſtate, temper, age, calling, company, that ſo he may with the greater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage tempt to evil, and thereby bring Men into the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62133:15"/> ſame miſery and condemnation with himſelf. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed whoſoever duly weighes the perfect antipathy that is in Satan, both unto God and Holineſs, can hardly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in what other thing he ſhould exerciſe himſelf, then to tempt and ſolicit Men to ſin. For ſuch is the greatneſs of his malice, that, as the Schooles deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, it cannot admit any farther degree of augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, his will being immovably fixed to evill as its ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate end. Needs therefore muſt his malice and hatred diſpoſe him to the doing of ſuch evills as may bear a proportion to the greatneſs of it. And wherein can it in a higher way diſcover it ſelf, then in deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and effecting the ruine of the ſouls of Men by pernicious Counſells and devices? If there be any one thing in which ſo diſcontented a Perſon, as Satan is, can take delight, it is in his Trade of Seduction, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, in making others as irrecoverably loſt and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable as himſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> As tempting and enſnaring of Men is his onely buſineſs, ſo his diligence in it is matchleſs. He was going too and fro in the earth, and walking up and down in it in <hi>Jobs</hi> time, <hi>Job</hi> 1. 7. and in <hi>Peters</hi> time he was a roaring Lyon, walking about, ſeeking whom he may devour, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 8. The Beaſts of the earth, though they hunt after their Prey, yet when the Sun ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and Man goeth forth to labour, they gather them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together, and lay them down in their Dens, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 104. 22. But this infernal Lyon is reſtleſs in his motions, and compaſſeth the earth with as much unweariedneſs as the Sun doth the Heavens. It is true be tempts others to idleneſs, but himſelf is never idle. The Fowler is deſirous that the flying Bird would alight upon the ground, or perch upon ſome Tree; but all the while he is in motion, that when it ſo doth it
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62133:16"/> may the better become his mark: So the Devil, he doth what he can to lull others aſleep in idleneſs and ſloth; but he then ceaſeth not to ſhoot his darts, and to ſpread his ſnares. When <hi>Samſon</hi> was aſleep on <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilahs</hi> knees, ſhe cauſed his Locks to be cut off, <hi>Judges</hi> 16. 19. and wrought all that miſchiefe upon him, that terminated not in the loſs of his eyes, but in the loſs of his life. While the Servants ſlept the enemy came and ſowed his Tares, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 25. Oh! how well would it go with Chriſtians, if the diligence of their Adverſary would provoke them to watchfulneſs, and kindle in them an holy induſtry unto all good, that ſo they might approve themſelves to be <hi>Dei Milites,</hi> Gods Souldiers, to ſight againſt all evil: and <hi>Operarii Dei,</hi> Gods Workmen and Servants in doing all good. Sure it is their complaints would be fewer, and their comforts would be greater. But alaſs! what a ſad complaint may I now take up, and whileſt I ſpeak of the diligence of the Evill One, mourn over the ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and negligence of moſt Profeſſors, amongſt whom <hi>a waking Eye,</hi> and <hi>a working Hand</hi> are as rare to be found as a <hi>Sword</hi> and a <hi>Spear</hi> among all the People of <hi>Iſrael, 1 Sam.</hi> 13. 22? How few are there that have taken the alarum though they be called upon, ſo as to ſtand upon their Watch againſt temptations? How hard is it to perſwade Men that to walk circumſpectly is a duty? or, that to be diligent in their Callings is one of the beſt Antidotes to preſerve the Soul from the putrefaction of luſts, and to fence it againſt the Incurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of an Affiduous Tempter? It is a common Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb that the Lyon is not ſo ſierce as he is Painted; and it it a received opinion that the Devil is not ſo hurtfull an Enemy as he is repreſented to be. It is no wonder then if his deſigns be ſo ſucceſsfull, and his Triumphs
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62133:16"/> many, when the greateſt part of Men are no way anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to proportion their care and watchfullneſs, either to the greatneſs of their own danger, or their adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries diligence.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p>A Fourth Demonſtration, <hi>which may diſcover the power of Satan to tempt, is taken both from</hi> the <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> of the evil Spirits, and the <hi>Unity</hi> of their Counſels, which meet all in one common center of an irreconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable hatred to Gods glory, and Mans happineſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Their Numbers are great, which renders their Power, as well as their Counſells exceeding dreadfull. Weak things, which when few are contemptible, when ſeconded with multitude become irreſiſtable. Cater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillars, Frogs, Locuſts, Flies, by the exceſs of their number make the proud heart of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to ſtoop, who cannot free himſelf or his Kingdome from ſuch impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Adverſaries. The Whale, of which God ſaith, that <hi>upon the earth there is not his like: He is a king over all the children of pride, Job.</hi> 41. 33, 34. Of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures by Sea or Land, that pride themſelves of their might and ſtrength, he is the chiefe; and yet <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaith, that the Herrings do by their vaſt numbers op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs and deſtroy ſometimes the biggeſt Whales. How dreadful then muſt that oppoſition be, that ariſeth from ſuch creatures, that are for their nature powerfull, and for their numbers paſt finding out. The School men who would ſeem to be expert <hi>Benjamites</hi> to hit at a hairs breadth every mark at which they aime, and not miſs, ſpeak as confidently of the number of good and evil Angells, as if they had looked into the Muſter-Roll both of the Heavenly hoſt, and the Infernall Legions,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62133:17"/> and yet their aſſertions have as little agreement with each other, as the teſtimonies of the falſe Witneſſes concerning Chriſt, no two of them ſpeaking the ſame thing. <hi>Aquinas</hi> conceives the number of them in their Creation to exceed incomparably all material ſubſtances, and his reaſon, as <hi>Eſtius</hi> ſets it down, is, becauſe the more perfect any beings are in their nature, the greater is their exceſs, either of <hi>Magnitude,</hi> if they be corporeal, or of <hi>Number,</hi> if they be incorporeal. As therefore the Heavenly Bodies, which are moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, do wonderfully ſurpaſs all inferiour bodies in quantity; ſo do the ſpiritual Angells in number. Now of theſe vaſt numbers, ſay ſome, the one halfe become Apoſtates. Others, from a miſtake of that place, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 4. of the Dragons drawing of the third part of the Stars of Heaven after him, have fondly concluded, that a third part of them fell, when as it plainly ſpeakes of a defection in the Church. Others again have made the number of fallen Angells equall to the number of the elect Men that ſhall be ſaved, who are to ſupply the breach that was by their defection. But what light o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> evidence do any of theſe poſitions carry in them, that may gain the underſtanding of ſober Men to a beliefe of them? are they not nicities, that are as unfit to build upon as the dreames of ſick Men? It is enough that the Scripture, though it acquaint us not with the certain number of good or evill Angells, that of the one it tells us, that <hi>there are thouſand thouſands that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter unto God, and ten thouſand times ten thouſand that ſtand before him, Daniel</hi> 7. 10. And that there is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable company of Angells, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 22. And that it repreſents unto us the evill Angells by a <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> which implies multitudes; and by a <hi>Prince</hi> whoſe greatneſs lies to the extent of his condition, and the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62133:17"/> number of his Subjects. Surely we need no Hermits Viſions to inform us that the air is full of malignant Spirits, and the earth of their ſnares to entrap the inhabitants of it. St. <hi>Paul</hi> points out to us their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as well as their power, when he faith, that <hi>we wraſtle not with fleſh and bloud, but againſt principalities, against powers, againſt the rulers of the darkneſs of this World, againſt ſpiritual wickedneſs in high places.</hi> Eph. 6. 12. Oh! what a troubleſome paſſage muſt every Chriſtian expect in his way to heaven, who is to conflict with Armies of theſe infernal <hi>Anakims?</hi> How neceſſary is it that he put on the Armour of God for protection, and fight in the ſtrength of God to obtain a victory? For in his own might no man can prevail. If <hi>Elijah,</hi> a Prophet of an Heroick Spirit, complained of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing left alone to conteſt with the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> and the Idolaters of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo as to grow weary of his life, how apt will the beſt of men be to faint and ſink in the long and ſharp Conflicts, that muſt be undergone with the Combined forces and powers of darkneſs, if not aided and ſupported by the ſtrength of Chriſt? If therefore we would be ſucceſsful Combatants in this Spiritual Warfare, we muſt do as <hi>David</hi> did, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to encounter <hi>Goliah</hi> by diſarming himſelf of his warlike Habiliments, going forth only in the name of the Lord of Hoſts; we muſt put off all carnal confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which will be as unuſeful to us as <hi>Sauls</hi> Armour was to him, and be ſtrong only in the Lord, and in the power of his might, this is that that will both animate us in the fight, and give unto us an aſſured victory in the Iſſue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> As their <hi>Number</hi> is great, ſo their <hi>Unity</hi> and agreement is wonderful. In Satans Kingdom are no diviſions, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 26. In his Armies no mutinies
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62133:18"/> for want of pay, no complaints of hard marches, though they be continually compaſſing the earth to and fro. That there ſhould be an Union amongſt the heavenly Hoſt is not ſtrange, in regard they are all as ſo many melodious Inſtruments tuned to one Key; as ſo many Needles touched with the ſame Loadſtone, which fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them invariably to one point: they dwell with him, and in him who is love it ſelf. But is it not matter of admiration, that an entire oneneſs, which is ſo much wanting on earth, ſhould be found in hell? What is Hell but the Common Sewer and Drain into which thoſe Luſts of Pride, Wrath, Envy, and Bitterneſs, from whence Wars do ariſe, do empty themſelves? Have Devils any love? Is there any print of that noble quality, which is as amiable as the Sun to be found in the territories of darkneſs? What then is that Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Cement, that ſo firmly ties and conjoyns them together? It is no other but a perfect hatred both to God and man, it being the one thing deſigned by them to rob God of his glory, and man of his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and to effect this the Conſpiracy is ſtrong, and League inviolable. The good Angels rejoyce at the converſion of a ſinner; and the evil Angels at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: The ruined ſinners are the only Trophies and ſpoyls of Hell. Oh! bluſh then ye Saints, who have ſo many Sacred bonds to unite you to God, and alſo to one another, and yet by Diviſions are ſet at a diſtance from each other, making the enemies vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, as the Hiſtorian ſpeaks, by your diſcords. Are you not all the Brethren of one Father, <hi>God bleſſed for ever?</hi> And of one Mother, <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which is above? <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Brethren of the <hi>whole bloud,</hi> like <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Benjamin?</hi> Have you not ſucked the ſame breaſts? And been nurſed up with the ſame
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62133:18"/> ſincere milk of the Word? Are you not all <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>joynt heirs</hi> of the ſame glorious <hi>inheritance</hi> reſerved for you in the heavens? Are you not led by the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, who is a Spirit of love and goodneſs, and doth not <hi>Generare accipitres, ſed columbas,</hi> beget <hi>birds of prey,</hi> but <hi>Doves</hi> whoſe Bills are never ſeen to be bloudy in the leaſt? Shall not then love effect that in you, which a curſed hatred doth in Devils? They are one by a Common principle of wickedneſs, which runs through them; and ſhall not you be one who are ſo cloſely knit together with ſo many and ſuch ſtrong ties? That the luſtful <hi>Goats</hi> ſhould puſh at one another is no matter of wonder, but that the tender <hi>Lambs</hi> ſhould doſs and ſtrike at each other cannot but be for a lamentation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. V.</head>
                  <p>A Fifth Demonſtration of Satans power and ability to tempt, is, <hi>From his great and ſtrange artifice to convey ſuggeſtions to evil after ſuch a manner into the heart, as that they cannot be diſtinguiſhed from the luſtings and ebullitions of depraved nature.</hi> It is not only difficult to find out any certain Character between <hi>Malum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatum, &amp; innatum, morſum ſerpentis, &amp; morbum mentis;</hi> The evil that is ſown, and the evil that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, between the bitings of the Serpent, and the diſeaſe of the mind, as <hi>Bernard</hi> expreſſeth it; but it is, as he conceiveth, wholly impoſſible: He profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that after much ſearch and ſtudy he could never clearly know, <hi>Quid cordi, quid hoſti tribunt,</hi> what he may charge upon his heart, and what upon the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Now his advantage of thus inſinuating, and wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf into the boſome doth much promote and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62133:19"/> further a compliance with his ſuggeſtions, becauſe men are more apt to be ſwayed by ſuch thoughts which they look upon as the naturall births of their own hearts, than ever they would be by ſuch which they diſcern to be ſorrain, and to be injected from an irreconcilable and a ſworn Enemy. If any Print or Signature of Satan did in the leaſt appear in his ſuggeſtions, by which the tempted might diſcover when the motions to any ſin did come from him, and when from themſelves, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his ſucceſs not their danger would either of them be ſo great by far as now they both are. For it cannot be reaſonably imagined that any ſhould ſo readily cloſe with, or hearken un<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o what they find him to be the Prom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter of, as to what they deem to have its riſe from their own breaſt, without any other mover than themſelves. The bird takes the Egg or Young for its own, though laid or put into the neſt by another hand, which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it doth with an unwearied diligence both hatch and feed; but if it ſhould once deſcry it to be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, it would forthwith caſt it out and deſtroy as ſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. And ſo thoſe ſinful motions, which are injected into mens hearts by the evil one, but reputed by them to be no other than the natural births of their own minds, are more dandled in their thoughts, and ſooner gratified by an actual compliance than ever they would be, if diſcovered to have their original from the Tempter. When Satan ſtood up againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and provoked <hi>David</hi> to number the People, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21. 1. It was not by making ſuch impreſſions, as might evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence him to be the Counſellour of the fact, but by exciting ſuch affections of vain-glory and ſelf-confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which naturally abound in the hearts of Princes when their Armies are victorious, and the face of their Affairs like a ſerene Sky without any mixture of Clouds.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62133:19"/> Thus <hi>Benhadad</hi> grows in his demands upon <hi>Ahab,</hi> as if he would try what it was that he dares deny, by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a ſecond Meſſage to his firſt, in which he inlargeth the terms of his ſubmiſſion to the ſearching of his houſe, and the houſes of his Servants, and the taking away of whatſoever is deſirable in their eyes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing refuſed the doing of it, he proudly boaſts, that the duſt of <hi>Samaria</hi> ſhall not ſuffice for handfuls for all the people that followed him, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19. 10. And ſo <hi>Senacherib,</hi> fleſhed with the many Conqueſts that he had obtained over divers Nations, ſwells with pride, till he breaks into blaſphemy: <hi>Who are they among all the Gods that have delivered their Country out of my hands, that the Lord ſhould deliver Jeruſalem out of my hands? 2 Kings</hi> 18. 35. Yea, good <hi>Hezekiah</hi> had his heart ſo far lifted up within him by the fulneſs of his Treaſures, and the multiplicity of his proviſions both for War and Peace, as that he vainly boaſts of them to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours of the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> 2 Chron. 32. 31. And from ſuch latent ſeeds of pride, which breed in the beſt of hearts, as moths in the fineſt garments, did Satan kindle this inordinate deſire in <hi>David,</hi> of his knowing the number of his warlike forces, which the juſt expoſtulations of <hi>Joab</hi> and the Captains of the Hoſt could not allay. He delighted in this thing, and <hi>the Kings word prevailed,</hi> 2 Sam. 24. 3. Thus alſo in tempting of Chriſt, he makes uſe of <hi>Peters</hi> natural af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to his Maſter to diſſwade him from ſuffering death, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 22. Little did <hi>Peter</hi> ſuſpect that the words which he ſpake, Satan prompted, and that he was but an Inſtrument to convey the poyſon of a temptation as black as hell into his Saviours boſome, the conſequences of which would have been more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal than if the Stars had dropt from heaven, and the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62133:20"/> Sun been blotted out of his Orb, or the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had become as ſhrivelled Parchment before the fire. For what had become of all the Choſen of God, muſt they not have died in their ſins, if Chriſt had not died for their ſins? Muſt not heaven have been empty of glorious Saints within, though thick ſet with gliſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Stars without? Muſt not the work of Redemption have been like the ſtructure of an unwiſe builder, who began to build, but never finiſhed what he had begun? But alas all theſe aſtoniſhing evils were not in the leaſt diſcerned by <hi>Peter,</hi> much leſs deſigned. Little did he think of being a Tempter to his Lord, or of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuch a check from Chriſt, as to have his name gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to him whoſe work he did: <hi>Get thee behind me Satan.</hi> And in this myſterious and hidden way doth he ſtill manage his ſuggeſtions both in the hearts of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, and others alſo, that ſo their compliance might be the more facile to the evil to which he tempts, while he is not detected to be the firſt mover to it. Old <hi>Iſaac</hi> would not have been perſwaded to have eaten of <hi>Jacobs</hi> Veniſon, though he greatly loved it, if that he could either by queſtioning him who he was, or by feeling his hands, have diſcerned him not to be his Son <hi>Eſau.</hi> So thoug<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> men have a ſecret liking to the ſin to which they find themſelves moved, yet if the inſtigations unto it did appear to them to come from Satan, it would rather make them tremble, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> did when <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſubtilty was found out, than any waies beget in them further hankerings to haſten the fulfilling of it. But that which makes the myſtery of theſe his undiſcerned impreſſions the more ſtrange is, that though in the ſame temptation he reiterate the deception again and again, yet is it not more perceived by us at the laſt than it was at firſt. We are ſtill at as great a loſs to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62133:20"/> trace out any difference between his <hi>injections,</hi> and the natural <hi>luſtings</hi> of the heart to evil, as we ſhould be to find the path of a Serpent upon a Rock, who though he paſſeth often over it, yet leaves not, as worms and ſnails do any filth or ſlime behind him that may deſcry his various and crooked windings.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VI.</head>
                  <p>A Sixth Demonſtration, with which I ſhall ſhut up this firſt general Head of Satans ability to tempt, is <hi>from the ſutableneſs that is between his Suggeſtions and corrupt reaſon.</hi> He cannot in the leaſt offer violence to the ſoul, or break in upon it by a forcible entry whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it will or no; The <hi>body</hi> may be liable to his vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, but not the <hi>ſoul.</hi> The Aſſertion of <hi>Bonaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> is a truth, <hi>Inducit Diabolus, immutat Deus, nemo cogit.</hi> The Devil may allure, God only can effectually change, but none can compel us. When therefore he tempts to ſin, he inſinuates himſelf by ſuch <hi>Topicks</hi> that are pleaſing to Carnal Reaſon, and apt to beget a ready compliance with his ſuggeſtions. <hi>Prophane</hi> and <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> wretches he bears in hand that Religion is but a cunning and deviſed <hi>Fable,</hi> a meer <hi>Scare Crow,</hi> ſet up by Preachers to keep ſimple and weak People in <hi>awe;</hi> That <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> things ſo much ſpoken of, are but <hi>imaginations,</hi> the one a <hi>pleaſing dream,</hi> and the other a <hi>falſe fire,</hi> that frights more than it hurts, and that they which ſeem to dread it moſt, are yet ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times venturous enough to do ſuch things from which a flaming <hi>Tophet</hi> ſhould wholly reſtrain them. Now what dry rinder ſenſual hearts are to ſuch ſuggeſtions that fall upon them as ſparkes, who can be ſo blind, as not to perceive? Are not their ſecret wiſhes? Oh I
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62133:21"/> that there were no God to judge them, no hell or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of burning flames to torment them? Do they not what they can to cut off the hand of Conſcience that it may not ſmite them? And to put out its eyes that it may not ſee them? How eaſily then are they drawn into that opinion which they would gladly have to be a truth? And how juſtly left of God to ſuch horrible deluſions, that ſinning without fear they may periſh without remedy? Others again, who by Convictions are awakened to ſome more ſerious apprehenſions of God and Religion, by ſpecious ſuggeſtions he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades that the ſtrictneſs of life, which ſome few pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend unto, is but an affectation of ſingularity, in which they ſtrive not ſo much to be like God, as to be unlike their neighbours, that it is an heavy yoke which they put upon themſelves, and none of that <hi>eaſie yoke and light burden,</hi> which Chriſt commands them to take upon them. They need not fear but that they ſhall ſpeed well enough though they be not ſo ſcrupulous as others, who ſtick at every ſmall matter, as if Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſiſted altogether of Punctilioes, and could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be obtained without an Arrival at the higheſt pitch of Sanctity. If they pray ſometimes when they think of it, read the Scripture when their leaſure beſt ſerves them, and ſee the Church now and then in fair wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it is as much as needs. Are not theſe whiſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of the Serpent of an enchanting nature? Are not theſe kind of reaſonings ſured to moſt mens tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, who in Religion affect rather to diſcover that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible point where <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> part, than to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue after the attainment of a perfect ſtature in holineſs? Who think that a taſte of Godlineſs, like a little <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick</hi> on the knives point is more deſirable than the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it a mans dayly food? The Verſe in <hi>Gellius,</hi>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:62133:21"/> which <hi>Lipſius</hi> in his <hi>Politiques</hi> ſaith pleaſeth him, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentem oportet eſſe, religioſum nefas,</hi> hath many more approvers of it than himſelf, who deem a ſlight tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Religion uſeful to themſelves, and yet nauſeat as ſome abominable thing, the deep and double dye of it, ſo as to have it like a prevailing principle to give a Law and Rule to their whole Converſation. As then the ground becomes fruitful, not by <hi>receiving,</hi> but by <hi>liking</hi> of the Seed that is caſt into it, ſo Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions become ſucceſsful, not by the hearts bare recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, but by its ſecret reliſhing and affecting of them. If Satan, who is the evil Seeds-man, ſcatter any ſeeds of Temptations, to which the heart is <hi>Solum ſubactum,</hi> as a prepared and diſpoſed ſoyl by the corrupt principles that lodge in it, they will quickly ſprout forth into acts, and grow into a root that will bear G<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll and Wormwood. Can I then better put a period to this firſt General than by giving the good Chriſtian a brief, yet ſerious Caution, of liſtening to thoſe corrupt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings, with which Satan doth often feather thoſe Arrows of Temptations, that are ſhot out of his Bow, that they may the better reach the mark to which they are directed? Man is a Reaſonable Creature, and is apt to be ſwayed by any thing that carries a ſemblance of Reaſon, and if ſin come in any ſuch dreſs, the Will is ſoon gained to embrace the motion, and the ſin it ſelf to be finiſhed, which the Apoſtle tells us bringeth forth death, <hi>James</hi> 1, 15.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:62133:22"/>
               <head>Chap. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Containing an Enumeration of Satans Wiles.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Now come to the Second Part of my deſigned task, which is to diſcover the Policies and Devices of this Grand Maſter of Craft, not by compiling an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire body or <hi>Syſteme</hi> of them, or undertaking to give an exact and juſt account of their Number, which is a work as hopeleſs as the telling of the ſtars, and calling of them by their names; but the ſingling and chooſing out of the full heap, ſome which in the Spiritual Warfare are of moſt frequent uſe, and of greateſt danger, that ſo every Souldier of Chriſt, who is engaged in it, may ſee what need they have to exerciſe watchfulneſs, as well as courage, having to do with ſuch an Adverſary, who is no leſs active in his Subtilties, than impl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cable in his Malice. <hi>Malo cautior eſſe quam fortior, fortis ſaepe captus eſt, cautus rariſſimè.</hi> I had rather be cautious than valiant, the valiant are often enſnared, but the cautious ſeldom.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, It is a pernicious device and wily ſtratagem of Satan, <hi>To tempt by method, and by the practiſe of leſſer ſins to make the way more facile for the commiſſion of greater.</hi> He caſts down none ſuddenly from the Pina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of an high profeſſion into the loweſt Abyſs of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62133:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> wickedneſs, but leads them rather by oblique deſcents and turnings, lower and lower, untill their ſteps at laſt take hold on hell. The beginnings of ſin, as well as of grace, may fitly be reſembled to a grain of Muſtard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed, which is of all ſeeds the leaſt; but the growth of it is ſuch, that the birds of the air come and lodge in the branches thereof. Sin appears at firſt like <hi>Elijahs</hi> Cloud, and afterwards darkens the whole face of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: Or is as the head of a River, which hath nothing of <hi>breadth</hi> or <hi>depth,</hi> yet by its running encreaſeth and ſwells into the ſimilitude of a Sea: Small offences by Satans induſtry become the Parents of ſignal Crimes. Hath not anger, which ſets no other bounds to it ſelf than bloud and death, taken its riſe from a ſmall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt or diſlike; as ſometimes a mortal Gangrene from a ſlight prick of an Artery? Have not compleated im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purities often derived themſelves from the glance of a wanton eye? Or from ſome light and fooliſh geſture? What was the beginning of thoſe complicated ſins in <hi>David,</hi> his <hi>Murder</hi> and <hi>Adultery,</hi> was it not an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hallowed look? Did not Luſt, which like a <hi>moral Jaundice</hi> ſpreads its deformity over the whole man, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it ſelf at firſt in the Eye? It is <hi>Calvins</hi> Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, that the Kingly Prophet in thoſe Expreſſions, <hi>Pſalm 1. Of walking in the counſel of the ungodly, of ſtanding in the way of ſinners, and ſitting in the ſeat of the ſcornful,</hi> points out how by little and little men turn aſide from the right way. Firſt, they hearken to wicked Counſels and Sollicitations to ſin, which are as the ſeed of evil actions; and then the Devil enticeth them to joyn themſelves in fellowſhip with ſinners, till at length they become proud mockers, ſcorning both the reproofs of men, and the Judgments of God; and through depraved principles of Conſcience, ſpeak
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62133:23"/> good of evil, and evill of good. Now, how this gradual manner of Satans tempting ſerves his deſign of drawing men to ſins of the greateſt ſcandal and preſumption, we may eaſily ſee if we do but conſider that leſſer ſins make way for greater four waies.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, By way of deception, little ſins men conceive of, as they do of ſlight diſtempers of the body, that if need be are ſoon maſtered and overcome; an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary <hi>Apozem</hi> or decoction, a gentle Sweat, or a few Meals abſtinence, are preſcriptions valid enough to make a clear riddance of the one; and a reſolution or two taken up, of leaving what hath been done, or of doing otherwiſe than before, will as readily cure the other. But there is no Cuſtome ſo weak that hath not more power over our nature than we intended firſt to give it, inſomuch that many have been over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born with thoſe actions, the effects whereof they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to be at their own diſpoſe. For as Children turn round ſo long in ſport till at laſt they fall down when they would ſtand, ſo there are many who indulging themſelves in little ſlips and failings, bring themſelves to ſuch an evil dizzineſs of mind as throws them down when they purpoſe to ſtand and to break off from the paths in which they walked. When therefore a man finds that he is tempted to ſin becauſe it is little, and may at any time be as eaſily left as taken up, let him look upon it as a double impoſture of the Devil, who if he make it ſeem little in or before the doing of it, can make it appear much greater when it is done: Or if he would perſwade him that it may without diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty be left, let him remember there is a wide diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between running up a hill, and running down a hill; he that runs up a hill may ſtop when he will, but not ſo if he runs down: So if a man be climbing the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62133:23"/> hill of grace he may ſit down, or ſlack his pace as he pleaſeth, and ſhall not want happily Arguments good ſtore to move him to it; but if he be once ſtepping down the hill of a bad life, he can hardly give over till he come to the very bottom of it, till he hath <hi>finiſhed his ſin,</hi> which when it <hi>is finiſhed brings forth death, James</hi> 1. 15.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, By way of <hi>diſpoſition.</hi> Small ſins are as the <hi>priming</hi> of a Poſt or Pillar, that prepare it for the better receiving of thoſe other Colours that are to be laid upon it, and in which it is to ſtand: or as the prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious dippings of the wooll in divers liquors, that it may drink in more fully the tincture of the Scarlet. They beget powerful inclinations in the ſoul to greater ſins, and make a way for their entrance by corrupting mens apprehenſions of ſin, both in reſpect of its <hi>deformity,</hi> and its <hi>Magnitude,</hi> no ſin being equally <hi>gaſtly,</hi> and big to look on to him that admits of fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity with the leaſt of ſins, as to him that abſtains from all appearance of evil. It is <hi>Joſephus</hi> his Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, That <hi>Solomons</hi> foul defection to thoſe ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious impieties of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and <hi>inordinate love of many ſtrange women,</hi> did take its beginning from ſome leſſer ſlips and failings againſt the Law of God; as his ſetting the Brazen Sea upon twelve Oxen, and making the Figures of <hi>Lions</hi> and <hi>Cherubims</hi> upon the borders of it. And to him, and other ancient <hi>Hebrews,</hi> who are of the ſame Opinion, doth <hi>Grotius</hi> incline, adding alſo his <hi>multiplying of Chariots and horſes</hi> againſt the expreſs Command of God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10. 17. as another lapſe in the way before his ſtrange departing, and forſaking of the way. I ſhall not make it my work to determine what ſpecial warrant <hi>Solomon</hi> might have for what was done by him about things of the Temple, which would
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62133:24"/> free him from that part of the Charge; but this I think that whoſoever ſhall look into his Penitential Book of the <hi>Preacher,</hi> may eaſily find that his Fall was not Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular, and ſuch which at once caſt him as low as ever any of the Holy Men of God fell, but a ſinking and ſliding downwards by degrees; and from him learn, who was the Wiſeſt Man that ever was or ſhall be, that <hi>it is not wiſdome that will keep a Man from the worſt of ſins, if he once allow, or favour himſelf in leſſer evills.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, By way of <hi>Subſtraction,</hi> and withholding of that which may hinder the Commiſſion of greater ſins, the powerfull preſervatives againſt preſumptuous evils are an awfull fear of God, and a heart touched with the due ſenſe of ſin; <hi>How can I do this great wickedneſs and ſin againſt God,</hi> was <hi>Joſephs</hi> Plea to his Miſtriſs, when ſhe tempted him to folly, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39. 9. and <hi>Davids</hi> heart, when tender ſmote him for an irreverent touch of <hi>Saules</hi> garment, as well as for the cruell Murder of Uri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 5. Now both theſe will a cuſtomary living in ſmall ſins waſte and deſtroy, by making the heart brawny and ſtiff: a path that is trodden onely by the foot of a Childe, will, by its often going upon, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract a hardneſs as well as the beaten Road, and ſo will the heart in which little ſins have a common paſſage too and fro, as well as the heart that is as the high-way that leades to deſtruction; for all ſin hath the ſame tendency, though it do not work the effect in the like degree. As then they who would keep themſelves from a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed Stone, uſe daily helpes to carry away the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler gravell, ſo to prevent a flinty and obdurate heart, the care muſt be conſtant, and the practiſe frequent of purging the converſation from little ſins. Oh, if once the exerciſe of this duty be neglected, it can hardly be imagined how ſuddenly Men come to do worſe than
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62133:24"/> ever. Whence is it that Men ſport themſelves in the commiſſion of thoſe ſins, at the mention of which they would once have trembled? and brutiſhly wallow in the midſt of that mire, the leaſt ſpeck of which they would not formerly ſhould have been found upon their garments? Is it not from their compliance of leſſer ſins, that make them grow regardleſs of greater? Is it not from their neglect of the fear of God, a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Antidote againſt the growth of ſin? this is made the cauſe by God himſelf of <hi>Iſraels</hi> multiplyed wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Jer. 9. 3. They proceed from evill to evill, and they know not me ſaith the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, By way of <hi>Palli<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ion and hiding them when done.</hi> All ſin, as it hath <hi>death</hi> for the w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ges of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 23. ſo it hath <hi>ſhame</hi> for the companion of it; thence it is that Men ſeek to cover one ſin with another, deem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it better to be guilty of two faults, then to be evict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of one. And uſually a greater ſin is made the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering of a leſſer, as the vizard which is worn to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe and hide a Perſon, is more deformed then the Face that it is put upon. <hi>Sarah</hi> at the Angells Tidings that ſhe ſhould have a Childe <hi>laughed,</hi> and when he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves it, ſhe denies it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 15. to hide one ſin ſhe commits another, ſhe tells a <hi>lye</hi> to free her ſelf from the charge of <hi>laughter.</hi> And this ſecond ſin, if cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances be weighed, will be found greater then the firſt. <hi>David,</hi> to conceale his Adultery with <hi>Bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba</hi> covers it with the Murder of <hi>Uriah</hi> her Husband: A ſtrange Fig-lea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e to ſpread over ſo ſoule a Crime; but whether will not the ſhame of ſin drive a Man? if ſo holy a Perſon as <hi>David</hi> make this his ſecurity, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving done evill to do worſe. And thus alſo that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Woman <hi>Eudocia</hi> the <hi>Empreſs,</hi> and Wife of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius the younger,</hi> (as <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> relates the Story)
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62133:25"/> having an Apple given unto her by the Emperor of a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful bigneſs, that had been preſented unto him as a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſhe beſtowes it upon <hi>Paulinus,</hi> a learned Perſon; and for that cauſe of great intimacy and familiarity with her, he not knowing from whom the <hi>Empreſs</hi> had received it, tenders it to the <hi>Emperour,</hi> hereupon the <hi>Emperour</hi> ſendeth for his Wife, asketh her for the Apple, ſhe fearing becauſe of his earneſt enquiring after it, that her giving it away might diſpleaſe the <hi>Emperour,</hi> made anſwer, that ſhe had eaten it; he urged her to tell the truth, ſhe ſwore that ſhe had eat it: upon this the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed <hi>Emperour</hi> brings forth the Apple as a Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny againſt her, and in his jealouſie killed innocent <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus,</hi> and hated his Wife, who before was greatly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved by him. Is it not then matter of complaint as well as of wonder, that this practiſe ſhould be the common ſalve that many uſe to make others to deem them innocent when they have done evill, to add to denialls oathes, curſes, and bitter imprecations, of themſelves, little regarding what guilt they contract before God, ſo they may but ſeem blameleſs before Men. But let ſuch know, that they ſow the Winde, and ſhall reap the Whirle-winde; and that as they cover one work of darkneſs with another, God ſhall add one judgement to another; and by the ſcorching flames of his Wrath ſhall make them to read the Truth of that divine Maxim, <hi>He that hideth his ſins ſhall not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> proſpor, but whoſo confeſſeth and forſaketh them ſhall have mercy, Prov.</hi> 28. 14.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:62133:25"/>
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>SEcondly, A ſecond device and circumvention of Satan is, <hi>A vexatious and reſtleſs importunity in ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to the doing of that ſin to which he tempts,</hi> In a temptation are three parts.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>Suggeſtion;</hi> or the caſting of evill thoughts into the Minde, <hi>John</hi> 13. 2. It is ſaid that the <hi>Devill put it into the heart of Judas</hi> to betray his Maſter; <hi>Immiſit ut ſagittam:</hi> He threw, as a Dart, that thought into him, finding it then a ſit ſeaſon both for him to make ſuch a Motion, and for <hi>Judas</hi> to receive it.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>Perſwaſion;</hi> or the backing of the ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion with Arguments, which may ſway the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to approve and incline the will to conſent to that evill as good. And then he preſſeth ſometime by way of <hi>Terror,</hi> propounding ſad events, that will undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly follow, if there be not a yeilding to do what is ſuggeſted. Thus many are moved to a practiſe of ſtealing and couzening, through a conceived fear of want and penury, which will elſe inevitably fall on them. Others unto lying and perjury, to preſerve their life and liberty, which may be otherwiſe hazarded, if not loſt. Thus <hi>Peter</hi> both denied and forſwore his Lord to ſave himſelf from that danger, which his being with him might otherwiſe have expoſed him unto. Sometimes by way of <hi>enticement,</hi> ſetting before them the profit and advantage that will accrew by their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance with his motion. And thus <hi>Ahabs</hi> Prophets, through the ſuggeſtion of a lying ſpirit, perſwaded him to go up to <hi>Ramoth-Gilead,</hi> becauſe of the proſperous ſucceſs that ſhould attend his undertaking, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22. 21. And with a far more alluring bait would the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62133:26"/> have courted our Saviour, to have done homage and fealty unto him, by promiſing to inveſt him in a right to all the Kingdomes of the World, upon that ſingle condition, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. 9.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, The laſt part is a vehement and continued <hi>inſtigation</hi> to put in a ſpeedy execution what is ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and this is the utmoſt extent of Satanical Power, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21. 1. It is ſaid Satan ſtood up againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and provoked <hi>David</hi> to number the People: The <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riack</hi> renders it, <hi>Praecipitem tulit Davidem;</hi> He hurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>David</hi> headlong, not by compelling him, but with inſtance, again and again inforcing the motion till it was effected, notwithſtanding <hi>Joabs</hi> juſt expoſtulations and averſeneſs to it. The Fencers rule which (ſaith <hi>Lypſius)</hi> is <hi>repete</hi> double, and follow the blow when made, is Satans practiſe to the tempted, who purſues oft times his ſuggeſtions with that violence, as to rob them of their ſleep, that they may wake to his tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to urge them, whether in company or alone, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their callings, and recreations, or in their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne duties to God, to give them no freedome nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpit, till he gaine that from them by importunity, which he could not by argument and perſwaſion. Now how powerfull a meanes this is to obtain an end when per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in, and after received denialls and repulſes, to turn oppoſition into a yielding, the Scripture will fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh us with full and pregnant evidence. What was it that drew from <hi>Samſon</hi> the diſcovery of that ſecret that coſt him his life, but <hi>Dalilahs</hi> reſtleſs importunity? <hi>who preſſed him daily with her wordes, and urged him, ſo that his ſoul was vexed unto death, Judges</hi> 16. 16. He whom the combined power of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> could not overcome, is foiled by the flattering ſolicitations of a Woman; ſo as to become both their laughter, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62133:26"/> their prey. What was it that made the <hi>unjuſt Judge</hi> in the Parable to reſolve of avenging the Widow of her enemies? but a fear, <hi>leaſt by her continuall coming ſhe ſhould weary him, Luke</hi> 18. 5. The Originall word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is very emphaticall, which <hi>Beza</hi> renders, <hi>Ne me obtundat;</hi> leaſt ſhe ſhould <hi>beat</hi> or <hi>buffet</hi> him. It is the ſame with that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor. 9. 27. I keep under my Body, and bring it into ſubjection,</hi> alluding to the <hi>Roman Ceſtus,</hi> in which kinde of Fight, or <hi>Cuffs,</hi> it was the aime of the adverſary to bring each other to ſtoop and fall under his blowes. Yea our Saviour ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to aſcribe a more prevailing power to <hi>importunity</hi> then to <hi>friendſhip,</hi> that the one will <hi>extort</hi> what the other cannot <hi>intreate,</hi> Luke 11. 8. <hi>I ſay unto you, though he will not riſe and give him becauſe he is his friend, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his importunity he will riſe and give him.</hi> Can it then be matter of wonder to any Chriſtian, as if ſome ſtrange thing had befallen him, to find himſelf not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tempted to evill, but inceſſantly preſſed with vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency to the doing of it? Or need he, as not knowing the cauſe of his trouble inquire as <hi>Rebekkah</hi> did, <hi>Why am I thus?</hi> Is not Satan a ſubtile enemy? and is it not his deſigned aime to make the life of every believer <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable,</hi> or <hi>unholy?</hi> the one by an irkſome impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to evill, the other by a conſent and yielding to the doing of it? Is it not one of his ar<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s and methods to work a deſpondency in thoſe that reſiſt him, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing his aſſaults after a long and tedious conflict, in which they have born up againſt him, that ſo deſpair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be Conquerours, they may yield themſelves Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives? yea hath he not by this policy ſtaggered many Chriſtians; ſo as to make them ſay, <hi>Malum illud ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum, victus ſum,</hi> that evil word (as <hi>Pariſienſis</hi> calls it) I am overcome? and ſo to chooſe rather to do the ſin,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62133:27"/> then any longer to endure the trouble of his aſſaults. True it is haply that ſuch who have not experienced the continued violence of Satans inſtigations in this kind, of putting them upon the Commiſſion of a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſin, may judge it no hard task to perſiſt in the deniall of it, and to turne a deafe eare to all his Solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citations and Importunity, it being eaſie to conceive many things to be more facile then we finde them to be when aſſayed. But to them who thus think, let me recommend a due weighing of theſe three conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>The frailty and weakneſs of the Fleſh;</hi> which can as ill bear long temptations, as long afflictions: What the length of afflictions will expoſe unto, <hi>David</hi> hints to us, when he ſaith, <hi>The rod of the wicked ſhall not reſt upon the lot of the righteous, leaſt the righteous put forth their hands unto iniquity,</hi> Pſalm 125. 3. And will not the rod of the <hi>wicked one</hi> do as much by its long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance? The Devill knoweth (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) that we are earthen Veſſels, which cannot alwayes bear multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied knockes, and violent ſtroakes; and therefore thoſe of whom he cannot obtain his will by force, and fraud, he ſeeketh to overcome by a continued impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, and this way he vanquiſheth many, who want <hi>patience</hi> to endure, though they have at firſt <hi>courage</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>The art that Satan mingleth with his vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence;</hi> His urgency, is not to a <hi>courſe</hi> and way of ſin, but to the ſingle <hi>act</hi> and commiſſion of it. That which is often repeated and ſayed over by him in his preſſing of it, is, do it but once, try this time onely, Why not once? Why not now? Is it not better to eaſe our ſelves of the vexation by yielding once to the motion, then to be alwayes under it? He knowes that if a ſin be once
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62133:27"/> committed it will leave a proneneſs to do it again: and if the terrors of doing of it, which are commonly greateſt at firſt, be once broken through, it will not be a matter of difficulty to obtain the conſent to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it the ſecond and third time, becauſe the heart muſt needs be leſs bent againſt it in Prayer, and the power of grace and faith leſs vigorous to reſiſt it, when weakened by yielding to ſin, Conſcience alſo leſs tender and affected with the ſenſe of it.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <hi>The inequality of temper which is in the beſt;</hi> Grace that makes the oppoſition to Temptations, that are both violent and long, doth not alwayes work alike in the Soul, no more then the Pulſe beates alike in the Body; it hath ſometimes operations that are quick and ſtrong, and at other times ſuch as are ſlow, and languid, there being none that ſtand quite out of the ſhadow of ſin, though out of the region of death. Can it therefore be an eaſie work to bear up againſt Satans preſſing inſtigations unto evill, when the ſpiritual part is often clogged, and made leſs active by the Fleſh, yea, when it is weakened by its treachery? Surely were it not that the bowels of Chriſt were moved in him unto his when in ſuch a condition, as he was towards <hi>Peter</hi> when Satan deſired to have him, that he might ſift him as wheat, their faith would faile. Let me then beſpeak compaſſions for all thoſe, who labour under reſtleſs importunities of the Tempter, dayes, moneths, yeares, prompting them to ſome one ſin, being no more able to flee from them then to out-run them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or to caſt them off, then to ſhake off their own Fleſh. To any that have taſted the ſweetneſs of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, what can be more hatefull then daily inſtigations to ſin? And to ſuch who underſtand the bleſſedneſs of Communion with God, what can be more bitter, then
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62133:28"/> to find themſelves faſt chained as it were to a Devil, who makes ſuch applications of vile objects to their fancy continually, that they cannot turn in the leaſt from? If it were burthenſome to <hi>Antipheron Orietes,</hi> whom <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> reports to behold alwayes his own Image ſtanding before him; how irkſome muſt it needs be to a gracious heart, to be alwayes haunted with the ſpectacle and image of ſome ſin as black as Hell? May I not ſay then on their behalfe, what <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> ſpake by his meſſengers to <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet, 2 Kings 19. 3. <hi>This day is a day of trouble, and of rebuke, and blaſphemy, wherefore lift up a Prayer for them:</hi> O Pray, that God would be their ſhield, and his power might be manifeſted in their weakneſs, that the Evill one might not touch them with any aſſimilating touch; who though he do <hi>moleſt</hi> them, may not yet <hi>defile</hi> them; and though he fight againſt them, may not yet prevaile over them; but that with the temptation God would make a way to eſcape, that they may be able to bear it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>A Third Device and Policy of the Prince of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; <hi>Tenebrifer</hi> not <hi>Lucifer</hi> (as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſtiles him) is, <hi>a ceaſing to tempt, or after ſome ſhort conflict to faigne a flight, not from neceſsity, but from deſigne.</hi> It is ſaid, Joſh. 8. 15. <hi>That Joſhua and all Iſrael made as if they were beaten before the Men of Ai, and fled by the way of the Wilderneſs:</hi> But it was to draw them from their fenced City into the Power of an Ambuſh, ſet to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare them: And this among other ſtratagems which <hi>Braſidas</hi> in <hi>Thucidides</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>belli,</hi> the thefts of War, Satan often uſeth, diſſembling a <hi>flight,</hi> that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62133:28"/> thereby he may the better ſteal a victory, and bring un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looked for miſchiefes upon thoſe from whom he ſeems to fly. <hi>Pariſienſis</hi> ſaith, it is <hi>omnium inſidiarum peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culoſiſsima,</hi> of all his ſnares and wiles the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous: becauſe that as he deſignes it for evill ends, ſo it ſeldome miſſeth of ſucceſs; few heeding to obſerve whether his flight be <hi>pretended,</hi> or <hi>reall;</hi> whether his ceaſing to tempt be out of <hi>skill,</hi> in order to ſome hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den deſign, or out of <hi>conſtraint</hi> cauſed by the <hi>reſiſtance</hi> of faith. I ſhall therefore indeavour to ſhow: Firſt, <hi>What Satan aimes at in his ſeeming flight:</hi> Secondly, <hi>How to diſtinguiſh it from that which is reall, and forced by the firme oppoſition which Faith makes againſt him, and the victory that it obtaines over him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> By this Policy <hi>he ſeekes to infect, and ſwell the heart with pride,</hi> which to keep down and deſtroy is one great end of Gods ſuffering his to be tempted. Pride is a ſin which it is hard to <hi>kill</hi> or to <hi>ſtarve,</hi> ſo ſutable a Soyle is the heart to nouriſh it above all other ſins whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and ſo apt is every occaſion to make it put forth afreſh; but nothing doth more quicken and actuate it then greater atcheivments. It is <hi>Tacitus</hi> his obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Rebus ſecundis etiam egregii duces inſoleſcunt,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Generalls are puft up with ſucceſs, eſpecially againſt an enemy of repute and eminency. And is there any adverſary that can contribute more to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry who puts him to ſlight, then the great Dragon, that old Serpent, called the Devill and Satan? Is not he the Prince of the Aire, and the God of the World? are not his Territories full of Captives, whom he hath mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably enthralled? Hath he not more Vaſſalls then Chriſt hath Subjects? Muſt it not then be matter of juſt glory and triumph, to defeate and overcome him, by whom ſuch multitudes are vanquiſhed? But yet as
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62133:29"/> he that ſtriveth muſt ſtrive lawfully; ſo he that glorieth muſt glory lawfully, which muſt be in the Lord, in the power of whoſe might he is made ſtrong, elſe his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying will be both his <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>ſnare.</hi> And this Satan ſo fully underſtands, as that in the heat of a Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he makes certain Ceſſations and unexpected re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirements, on purpoſe to deceive by the vain hopes of a ſuppoſed victory. And are not many by this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt lifted up, as if their Conflict were at an end, and the Field wholly won by them? Do they not pride and pleaſe themſelves in thinking how they ſhook off the infernal Viper with as much eaſe, and as little hurt to themſelves, as <hi>Paul</hi> did that Viper that came from the bundle of ſticks, and faſtened on his hand? Do they not ſlight others who complain of long and ſore tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations with which they are buffeted, as if they did ſpring rather from their weakneſs, than the power of the Tempter? Oh when men thus ſet imaginary Crowns on their own heads, how unlike are they to thoſe holy Elders who caſt their Crowns before the Throne of God, ſaying, <hi>Thou art worthy O Lord to receive glory, and honour, and power?</hi> And how like unto him whom they think they have foiled? By being tainted with that ſin of pride which caſt the Angels out of heaven, and condemned them to be reſerved in everlaſting Chains under darkneſs unto the judgment of the Great Day.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>By this Art he ſeeks to induce a ſpirit of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, and to poſſeſs the heart with vain preſumption of a future peace and freedom from his aſſaults,</hi> than which nothing can prove more fatal to a Spiritual Warfare. That ſaying of <hi>Epicharmus,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to diſtruſt, is more uſeful Counſel to none than to a Chriſtian when not frowned upon by the World, nor
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62133:29"/> moleſted by Satan; for changes will come both from the one and the other: The World will prove a falſe Friend, the Devil a true Tempter. After three ſharp repulſes given him by our Saviour, he departed only for a ſeaſon, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4. 13. And can we expect that he will be beaten out of heart, and made a Coward by us? When reſiſted, and put to ſlight again and again, he will return, if not to <hi>conquer,</hi> yet to <hi>vex.</hi> But no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will more haſten his return than a drowſie ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that is the ſeaſon which he watcheth for, that is the end of his ceaſing to tempt, and his ſeeming de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture; and when he finds us, like the men of <hi>Laiſh,</hi> living careleſs and at eaſe, <hi>Judg.</hi> 18. 7. then he ſmites, not as the good Angel did <hi>Peter,</hi> to awaken him, <hi>Acts</hi> 12. 7. but, as the fierce <hi>Danites,</hi> to kill and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy as much as in him lies. Then it is that he ſows thoſe noxious tares that come up afterwards to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice and hurt of the good Seed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 25. Then it is he comes and brings ſeven worſe Spirits with him, making the laſt ſtate of that man more miſerable than the firſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11. 26. Let none therefore pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a ſinful eaſe and reſt from temptations, as if the work were wholly done, when in truth nothing is done; but let them look how they come by it, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether it be not a <hi>practiſe</hi> of the Enemy, rather than a <hi>reality;</hi> whether it ſpring not rather from a <hi>ceaſing</hi> of the Tempter to ſtir, than from a <hi>victory</hi> obtained againſt him, now how to difference the one from the other is the next particular that I am to deſcend unto.</p>
                  <p>To find out therefore the truth of the one from the impoſture of the other, I will ſet down briefly theſe three Rules.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>Look what means and wayes of reſiſtance have</hi>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:62133:30"/> 
                     <hi>been uſed to put Satan to flight;</hi> Have inſtant prayers been made to God? Have the goings out againſt him been in the power and might of Chriſt? Hath the Sword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God, been ſet againſt the motions of ſin, and the preſſing inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of the Tempter? What is it that hath at any time been done to put a period to the Conflict? For as <hi>Livy</hi> ſaith, <hi>Stultitia eſt, ſedendo, ac votis debellari credere poſſe:</hi> It is a folly to believe that by ſitting ſtill, and naked wiſhes, Enemies can be conquered and overthrown: Victory attends upon the diligent and induſtrious, not upon the ſlothful. If then tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vaniſh and diſappear we know not how, and that no account can be given of the Calm and Peace that we do enjoy, as the fruits of prayer and other means uſed for the obtaining of it, we have cauſe to be jealous that the freedom and reſt we have is but an Artifice of the Adverſary to make us ſecure, and thereby the more eaſily to enſnare us: <hi>Nemo enim celerius opprimitur, quam qui nihil timet;</hi> none being ſooner vanquiſhed than he who fears nothing.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>When ever Satan is really worſted, ſin is wounded.</hi> He is never put to flight but Luſt receives a mortifying blow, for the fight is both made and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by Faith, and other graces of the Spirit, which carrie in them more immediate oppoſition unto ſin than unto Satan, it being the great work of every one that is begotten of God to keep himſelf that the <hi>wicked one touch him not,</hi> 1 Joh. 5. 18. Not that he tempt him not, but that he defile him not by any aſſimilating touch: And this is the only way by which a Believer can be ſaid both to reſiſt him, and alſo to overcome him; we cannot kill the Devil, nor weaken in the leaſt his power, but as we mortifie Luſts which are the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:62133:30"/> matter that he works upon, and the leſs of it he finds in us, the leſs able he is to hurt us. If therefore a Temptation go off, and the heart be not ſet more againſt ſin, ſo as to loath and hate it, which is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretative murder of ſin, as well as of our Brother, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 15. So as to pray and watch more againſt it, we cannot well conclude our reſt and eaſe to be good when it wants grace as its companion, and the quiet fruits of righteouſneſs as its evidence, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 11.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <hi>When the wicked one is overcome and driven to a flight, there will abide upon the ſoul a lively ſenſeof ſo great a mercy, which will manifeſt it ſelf in a deep appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of thoſe treacheries, and deceits that the heart did abound with in the hour of tryal,</hi> and a ſelf abhorrency for them in an humble and thankful acknowledgment of ſtrength and power from Chriſt, whereby it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to fight a good fight, and to obtain an happy vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, in a careful treaſuring up the experience it hath had of Gods faithfulneſs in its greateſt ſtraits, in a timely preparation and laying in of ſpiritual proviſions for another concounter, as knowing that its warfare will not be compleated till it come to heaven. Theſe, and ſuch like effects, are the iſſues of thoſe Temptations in which Satan is put to flight, and the ground of it is, becauſe it is done in the exerciſe of thoſe means and graces of the Spirit as alwaies leaves the ſoul in a better temper than it found it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p>A Fourth <hi>device of this ſpiritual Abaddon is touching the end and the means</hi> wherein he puts cheats upon thouſands, either by dividing between the one and the other, or by buſying them in the uſe of falſe and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:62133:31"/> ineffectual means to attain it, or by cauſing them to uſe good means in an undue and ſinful manner.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>It is a piece of Satans Sophiſtry to ſeparate between the means and the end,</hi> and to make men to preſume, that though the one be neglected the other may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; to this folly he would have tempted our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 6. When he ſet him upon the Pinacle of the Temple, he would have perſwaded him to have caſt himſelf down, and there given a proof both of his Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Gods fatherly care of protecting of him, but as it is a ſin to diſtruſt God in the want of means, ſo it is no leſſer ſin to preſume to be ſaved without them when they may be had; It is not an honouring of God by an abſolute truſt in him, but a tempting of him by a wanton pride in ſubjecting his power to act and work according to our pleaſure; but yet though Chriſt hath armed men againſt this Sophiſm of the Tempter by his own example, who would not betake himſelf to reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on God for ſafety in an extraordinary way, when not debarred of the common and uſual way. How great are the number of thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, who tempt God by unwarrantable practiſes, throwing themſelves into needleſs dangers and extremities that his power may appear in their deliverance and preſervation? <hi>Caſsian</hi> I remember tells a Story of three perſons, who in the confidence of Gods providing for them took a tedious journey into a Deſart, in which two of them miſerably died with hunger, the third only returned as a ſad ſpectacle of their folly. And <hi>Brentius</hi> hath a Relation of an Anabaptiſt Woman, who invited many Friends to Supper, but took no care to have any thing to ſet before them, fondly preſuming that the Table ſhould be furniſhed by God. But what are theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions, in which men thus divide between the end
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62133:31"/> and the means, any other than the ſcorn and laughter of thoſe who deride their folly, and yet through the ſeduction of the Devil become guilty of far greater. When they are Confident of heaven, and Careleſs of holineſs, they are ſecure of the end, and yet tread not one ſtep in the way that ſhould bring them to it. Are not theſe as vain as thoſe who expect a Harveſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Seeds time? Can any periſh with more clear ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convictions of Gods Juſtice in condemning them than theſe? Do they need to look into the Decrees of God to ſee the roots of their miſcarriage? Or into their own Conſciences? May not they ſay, the Serpent hath beguiled them, while they have hearkened to his Counſels, who was a lyar, and a murderer from the beginning?</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>The ſubtilty of Satan, touching the end and the means, is ſeen in his putting of men upon the purſuit of thoſe waies and mediums, which do not in the leaſt ſerve or conduce to that end for which they are uſed:</hi> So that though the intended end be good, yet they fall as equally ſhort of it, as thoſe who do nothing at all to obtain it, and are like miſguided Patients, who by their Medicines are not cured, but killed. And who can count the thouſands, or rather Myriads, that are held under the power of this deluſion of the Devil? May we not ask the moſt of thoſe who buſie themſelves in ſeeking a ſtate of happineſs, why do you lay out your mony for that which is not bread? Or why are you as thoſe who build in the fire, where the ſtructure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth as faſt as it is raiſed? Let us look abroad a little, and ſee if it be not a truth: And ſhall we need to take a view of that ſtrange and ſudden ſpread of <hi>Mahume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniſm?</hi> Where the Seductions of a bruitiſh Impoſtor have prevailed to the deluding of Nations and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62133:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> who have ſubjected themſelves to his Laws, and are drunk with the expectation of his carnal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes? Or ſhall we confine our Proſpect to the <hi>Roman Profeſsion</hi> of Religion? Who though they impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate ſalvation to themſelves, and exclude all others, who come not within the Pale and Verge of their Church, have yet dangerouſly ſwerved from the rule and path of life. <hi>Harlot</hi>-like they have laid the dead Child in the room of the living Child, their own cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt <hi>Fancies</hi> and <hi>Inventions</hi> in the place of Gods <hi>Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions,</hi> and in the obſervation of lying vanities forſake their own mercies. God hath ſet in the Church, not as a trimmed Lamp in the Sanctuary, but as the fixed Sun in the Firmament, the good Word of his Truth, to diſcover fully the knowledge of his Will, which is the juſt meaſure of all that obedience which he both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires and rewards: But they in this great <hi>Luminary</hi> have found, what ſome <hi>Aſtronomers</hi> have of late diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in the Sun, <hi>Vultum maculis infectum,</hi> A face ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with dark ſpots; and therefore charging it with obſcurity and defectiveneſs have betaken themſelves to unwritten traditions to be the guide and rule of their Faith as well as the Word, though all the light in them be but as the <hi>blaze</hi> of a Candle in the Socket that is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſweet nor certain. God hath ſtiled himſelf, <hi>A God hearing prayer, and that unto him all fleſh ſhall come, Pſal.</hi> 65. 2. But they have imparted this Divine Honour to Saints, for which they have neither <hi>Precept, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> or <hi>Example</hi> in the Scripture, robbing God of the glory of his goodneſs, whoſe arms are alwaies ſtretched out to receive thoſe that come to him in Chriſts name, whoſe bowels are ever yearning towards their neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ready to prevent their prayers with his bounty. And then what need can there be of heavenly
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:62133:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> Courtiers to render him more propitious to the fulfilling of their requeſts? God hath made eternal life to be of <hi>Grace,</hi> not of <hi>Workes,</hi> that it might be ſure, it is his gift, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 23. It is his Promiſe to them that love him, <hi>James 1. 12. Fecit ſe nobis debitorem non aliquid ànobis accipiendo, ſed omnia promittendo:</hi> He hath (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi>) made himſelf a Debtor, not by receiving ought from us, but by promiſing all unto us. But they going about to eſtabliſh their own righteouſneſs, have choſen rather to plead their title unto it by way of right and juſtice, and to aſſert a dignity and value in their Workes, to which the reward is due, not of Grace, but of Debt: Can we think theſe are apt <hi>Mediums</hi> to bring the Soul and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation together? or that they are not rather as Chaines of Glaſs more ſpecious then ſtrong? Are they not <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices</hi> rather then <hi>realities,</hi> brought in by thoſe, who in the Apoſtles Dialect are <hi>ſeducing Spirits?</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 2. And imbraced by thoſe who received not the <hi>love of the Truth that they might be ſaved?</hi> 2 Theſs. 2. 10 Have we not then juſt ground to depart from the Tents of theſe Men, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did from the Tabernacle of <hi>Ko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and to touch nothing of theirs, leaſt we be conſumed in all their ſins? They may return unto us, but we cannot return unto them; according to Gods command to the Prophet, <hi>Jer.</hi> 16. 19. Unleſs we ſhould change the Truth of God into a lie, and ſerve the Creature more then the Creator, who is bleſſed for ever.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The ſubtilty of Satan touching the end and the means, is ſeen, in making men to miſcarry in the uſe of right Meanes, by their uſing of them in an undue manner, and ſo to faile of the end for which they are appointed by God. And this is the way by which he prevailes over multitudes of Profeſſors, whoſe
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:62133:33"/> Duties, though done, daily prove wholly fruitleſs in the iſſue, becauſe of their heedleſs manner of performing them. Prayer is the key of bleſſing, which onely opens the Treaſures of heaven, both in regard of grace and comfort; and yet how many ask and receive not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ask amiſs? The eccho doth not return an anſwer to every ſound; no more doth God to every Prayer. Duties without life provoke God rather then pleaſe him; and gratifie Satan rather then trouble him. He cares not how much Men hear, or how often they Pray, if that he can but allay their intention and fervency in both, either by diſtracting their Mindes, or deading their Affections, ſo as to make them the <hi>Scele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> of duties, without a <hi>Soul</hi> to enliven and actuate them; naked <hi>formes,</hi> without any <hi>power</hi> of Godlineſs. How contemptible doth God ſpeak of his own Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, when done in a careleſs and looſe manner? When <hi>Iſrael</hi> came to appear before him, he asketh <hi>who hath required this at their hands to tread his courts?</hi> Iſai. 1. 12. <hi>Incenſe is an abomination, New Moones and Sabbaths he cannot away with,</hi> Verſ. 13. <hi>He curſeth them as deceivers that have in their Flock a Male, and ſacrifice unto the Lord a corrupt thing,</hi> Mal. 1. 14. And threatneth to <hi>ſpread the dung of their Solemne Feaſts upon their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> Mal. 2. 3. Is it not then matter of wonder as well as of complaint, that thoſe who own the appointed Ordinances of God to be the ſole Rule of giving glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to him, and obtaining good from him, ſhould yet for the moſt part ſatisfie themſelves in the doing of Duties rather then in the fruits they reap from them? Is it not an <hi>interpretative omiſsion,</hi> though not a <hi>formall neglect,</hi> to make that to be the task of the outward Man, which ſhould be the employment of the whole Man; to be the work of the Lip, which ſhould be the ſervice of the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:62133:33"/> heart? Will a Prayer, that is like an Arrow from a ſlack Bow, which never pierced the breaſt, ever pierce the Heavens? Will the hearing of the Word, in which the running Sands in the Glaſs are more eyed then the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, as giving hopes of a cloſe, ever convey its ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſuch an hearer? Will a Sabbath that is ſpent onely in the forbearance of Bodily Labour, without any Aſcentions of the Soul to God in holy Meditation, or Breathings after him in ſervent Prayer, either fill a Man with the fore-taſtes of Heaven, or make the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God in an eternal Sabbath to be deemed as his onely happineſs? And yet ſuch overlie Schemes, ſuch Bodily exerciſe, which profiteth not, are the Services which moſt give unto God, preſuming alſo that he is as well pleaſed with them as themſelves, whilſt through the Devils craft, and the deceitfulneſs of their own hearts, they look upon them as evidences to difference them from both the <hi>Prophane,</hi> who reject the thing that is good, and from the <hi>erroneous,</hi> who are led out of the right way by the Fancies and Inventions of Men.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. V.</head>
                  <p>A Fifth <hi>Device and Policy of Satan is his ſtrange and artificiall diſguiſing of objects, ſo as to make them to appear to be what they are not, yea, contrary to what they are in truth, and reality.</hi> When <hi>Tamar</hi> deſigned to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with <hi>Judah</hi> her Father-in-Law, ſhe put her Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes garments off from her, and attired her ſelf as an Harlot, and ſat in an open place, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 38. 14. that ſhe may the better effect her purpoſe, and what the iſſue was the ſtory tells us. So oftentimes when Satan would allure and tempt to ſin, he preſents the object, not in its naturall dreſs, but clothed in ſuch a manner,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:62133:34"/> as beſt ſuites with what he aimes at, as may be eaſily ſeen both in his <hi>attractives</hi> unto evill, and <hi>diſſwaſives</hi> from good.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>Evills which have a deformity inſeparably cleav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto them he hides and palliates Virtutis minio</hi> (as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes) by giving them a ſuperficial die and tincture of virtue, whereby he many times deceives the incautious, and ſerves alſo the hypocrite with ſpecious pretences: How doth the covetous <hi>Perſon, whom the Lord abhorreth,</hi> Pſalm 10. 3. pleaſe himſelf in his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did Parcimony, as if he onely practiſed frugality, and followed the Counſell of our Saviour, of <hi>Gathering up the fragments, that nothing be loſt?</hi> John 6. 12. With what a ſhew of Religion doth he deny bread to the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and cloathing to the naked, whileſt he ſhelters himſelf under the aſſertion of <hi>Paul,</hi> that if <hi>any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide not for his own houſe he hath denyed the Faith, and is worſe than an Infidel?</hi> 1 Tim. 5. 8. And yet his hand is ſhrunk up towards the one, as well as to the other. He turnes away from the ſtranger under a pretended care of Providing for his Family, and he robs them of their due neceſſaries, by making thrift a Cloak for his avarice. Is not alſo the <hi>Laodicean,</hi> or luke-warme Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, under the like deluſion, in regard of the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions he hath of his ſpirituall eſtate? Who is it that prides himſelf more in his moderation and diſcretion, as if he alone had hit the Golden Meane, and joyned the wiſdome of the Serpent, and the innocency of the Dove together, being not over-heated through the fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry paſſion of zeale, nor frozen and ſtupid through the diſſoluteneſs of Atheiſme and Prophaneneſs? And yet may not we ſay, that which is highly eſteemed among Men, is abomination in the ſight of God? hath he not expreſſed how irkſome ſuch a temper is to him,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:62133:34"/> when for this very cauſe he threatens an whole Church <hi>to ſpew it out of his Mouth?</hi> Rev. 3. 16. Yea, and ſeemes to wiſh it rather to be wholly cold, then to have ſuch an imperfect participation of both the extreames; not but that cold is more remote from heate then luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſs; but yet as it is a ſtate, or condition, it is worſe, becauſe Men are very rarely, and with great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty recovered out of it; being like to thoſe who lie in pleaſant Dreames, and are loath to be awakned out of them. It is <hi>Caſsians</hi> obſervation, which the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of others may ſeale unto as a truth; <hi>Ex frigido ſaepe fit calidus, &amp; calido quandoque frigidus, at rariſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè ex tepido ſit calidus;</hi> That oft times of cold one is made hot; and of hot ſometimes one returnes to be cold; but ſeldome or never do any from luke-warm come to be hot.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>As he allures to evill, by covering its defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity with his artificiall Paint and Varniſh, ſo as to entitle it to the name of a virtue, rather then of vice, or ſin;</hi> much like to a deceitfull Coyner that ſtamps the Kings Image upon his ſpurious Mettall, to make it paſs the more unſuſpected: <hi>So on the other hand, when he would diſſwade from good, he repreſents it under the most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible forme and appearance, to create ſuch prejudices and diſlikes againſt it, as may cauſe them to apprehend that it is naturally of that complexion in which it appeares to them;</hi> that by this meanes Men may ſcorne the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it, rather then imbrace the Practiſe of it, and look upon it as a thing that rather detracts from their worth and eſteem, then adds ought to it. No broken glaſs can render a beautifull Face more diſtorted and miſhapen, either by multiplying the parts, or miſplacing of them, then he doth the moſt amiable things of grace and holineſs. Is it not through Satans ſubtilty that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:62133:35"/> 
                     <hi>Religion</hi> it ſelf hath ſuch an unpleaſant aſpect in moſt Mens eyes? Is it not through the miſts that he raiſeth that it ſeemes to be a dark and opake <hi>body,</hi> and not a bright and glorious <hi>Luminary,</hi> which fills the breaſt in which it is ſeated with <hi>light</hi> and <hi>peace?</hi> It is he that ſuggeſts to the <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> that to diſdain it is a piece of <hi>reaſon;</hi> and to the <hi>Prophane,</hi> that to neglect the <hi>Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of it, though they own the <hi>Principles</hi> of it, is a point of <hi>Gentility.</hi> It is he that makes the World judge the <hi>zealous</hi> Chriſtian to labour of a Phrenzy, and the <hi>pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> Man, that beares injuries without revenge, to be a <hi>coward</hi> and ſtupid Perſon, that reſents not affronts; and he that exerciſeth ſelf-deniall to his unruly appetite, and curbes with a ſtrong reine the deſires of the Fleſh, to be no better then a <hi>Stoicall Foole,</hi> who ſeekes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Men to the condition of ſtocks and ſtones, and to extirpate all affections as excreſcencies of Nature, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to cheriſh them as its genuine offspring. O how powerfull are the arts and effaſcinations of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal <hi>Magician,</hi> who can thus make Men beſt pleaſed with that eſtate, in which they are <hi>rebells</hi> to God, and <hi>ſlaves</hi> to luſts; and from which they can expect no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but amazements, horrors, and diſtractions of minde, which will at one time or other afflict thoſe who proſtitute their Conſciences to ſuch impieties, as have in them the higheſt mixture both of <hi>folly</hi> and <hi>mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi> Have we not need to minde Men of Chriſts Counſell, <hi>Judge not according to the appearance, but judge righteous judgement,</hi> John 7. 24. When ſo many eaſily fall in love with guilded abominations, and greatly diſeſteem and ſcorn what is truly noble and Divine, by the uncouth <hi>vizards</hi> that are put upon it? Have we not need to ſet before Mens eyes that <hi>Woe</hi> that is denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt them <hi>that call evill good, and good evill, that</hi>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:62133:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                     <hi>put darkneſs for light, and light for darkneſs,</hi> Iſai. 5. 20. When not a few are under the power of ſtrong deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and believe a lie? Surely it is not unneceſſary in this Age of prodigious looſeneſs, wherein this impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of Satan hath ſo far prevailed, as that it is thought plea enough to defend the worſt of Debaucheries, and to vindicate them from cenſure, by the putting upon them ſome gay name; which is much at one, as if a Leper ſhould expect to be reputed clean, becauſe he hath co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered his foul Ulcers with coſtly Cloathing: or as if a Patient ſhould be in love with his diſeaſe becauſe the Phyſitian calls it by ſome name which he hath on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe invented to pleaſe his fancy.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VI.</head>
                  <p>A Sixth <hi>Device, or Machination</hi> (which like the <hi>net</hi> caſt on the right ſide taketh multitudes; or like the Bow of <hi>Jonathan,</hi> and the Sword of <hi>Saul,</hi> never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes empty) <hi>is Satans enſnaring of all ſorts of Perſons in the uſe of lawfull things.</hi> The Adage is not more common then true, <hi>Licitis perimus omnes;</hi> that we are undone by lawfull things, rather then by ſins: the ſmooth and deceitfull ſtream carries mo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e to the whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poole, which irrecoverably ſucks them in, then the rough and loud waters, which affright Paſſengers from venturing upon them; <hi>Oh this is a great ſnare.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Men can give no account of Time, Parts, States; but Hunting, Drinking, Hawking, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Satan by his art and cunning making Men to tranſgreſs the bounds in the uſe of Pleaſures, Recreations, nay even neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary things. Therefore take heed what you do, or how you walk, and be ſure to ſet boundaries to your ſelves, remembring that exceſs may turn that which is good
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:62133:36"/> into an abſolute evil; eating may become gluttony, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry in a Mans Calling may become covetouſneſs, recreations may become looſeneſs, when they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded, and not according to the rule and Warrant of the Word.</p>
                  <div type="advert">
                     <head>An Advertiſement to the Reader.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>VVHen the Reverend Author of this Diſcourſe had gone thus far, in giving this Work his laſt hand, it pleaſed God to p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t an end to his Conflict and Labours, and to call him to reſt in another World. Now becauſe it hath been an old trick (not to this day mended, though often complained of) to thrust forth Books into the World, either for Credit, or Profit, or ſome other deſigne, under the Names of ſuch Perſons as might make them more paſſable. Therefore it was thought ſit to give this</hi> Advertiſement.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, <hi>That the Authors own fair Copy reached no farther then the beginning of this</hi> Section.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, <hi>That the reſt that followes, is onely a colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction out of his looſe Papers and Notes; but it is all his own, without any Addition. Accept therefore</hi> (good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) <hi>what is here eſſayed towards the compleating this Work, out of his own Papers; which if the Author had lived to finiſh, thou wouldeſt have had more large and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act. The two laſt generalls which are propounded Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> II, <hi>are wholly omitted, becauſe nothing could be found about them in his own Papers.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:62133:36"/>
                  <head>SECT. VII.</head>
                  <p>THe ſeventh Wile of Satan is, <hi>ſuiting his temptations to the Ages and Conditions of men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Unto Ages: He obſerves Young Years, Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Age, Old Age; ſo alſo to the Ages in Chriſtianity, as the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſhews, 1 <hi>Epiſt. c. 2. 12, 13, v.</hi> where he writes to <hi>Babes, Young men,</hi> and <hi>Fathers,</hi> as thoſe that are ſubject unto ſeveral temptations, and ſo had need be cautelous.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Young men he tempts to Luſt and Wantonneſs, therefore <hi>Paul</hi> bids <hi>Timothy flee youthful luſts,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 22. And O that I might prevail with young men to poſſeſs their Veſſels in holineſs, and to remember their nature is that nature Chriſt hath taken on him. It is the Apoſtles Argument, 1 <hi>Cor. 6. 19. Your bodies are the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. He tempts middle Ages to a <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, he ſtirs up an itch of honour, and of being ſome great ones, of building their Families, and laying foundations of a name; and in this very ſnare many are caught, who by this very temptation have their thoughts, and minds ſo poſſeſſed, as that they wilfully reſiſt light, and put themſelves upon courſes, that turn away their hearts from God. It is the thought, and project of many a man, that after he hath feathered his neaſt, and done ſo, and ſo, he will bethink himſelf of his ſoul. Thus ſundry of the Popes ſought the Popedom by unlawful Arts, eſpecially <hi>Sylveſter</hi> the Second, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. He hath temptations for Old Age <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, Peeviſhneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> He obſerves the Condition of men as well as their Ages, and Conſtitutions, the Eſtates in which
<pb facs="tcp:62133:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> men are ſet. If men be afflicted and ſad in Spirit, ſuch he affrights with fears, and fancies, that are as gaſtly as the evils themſelves; A melancholly perſon, whoſe fancy is like a broken Glaſs, he fills with Jealouſies, Surmiſes, that make it ſwell as the Water of Jealouſie did the belly of the guilty woman. O a dark heart is Satans ſhop to hammer his temptations in. If a man is poor, then he tempts him <hi>to turn ſtones into bread,</hi> as he did Chriſt when he was hungry. If rich, then <hi>to turn bread into ſtones,</hi> that is the Devils Alchymy. Thus he works with mens States, Conditions, and with their Humours, and Paſſions, as <hi>Agrippina,</hi> when ſhe poyſoned her Husband <hi>Claudius,</hi> mingled the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with the meat which he loved moſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
                  <p>THe eighth device is, <hi>the inſinuation of many ſuggeſtions and temptations in ſuch an indiſcernable manner, and way, as that we cannot diſcern, and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence them from the reaſonings. and thoughts of our hearts,</hi> which if men could, they would not ſo eaſily hearken unto. <hi>Bernard,</hi> in his 32. Serm. on <hi>Cant.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nulli hoc mortalium poſsibile puto, ut diſcernat inter morſum ſerpentis &amp; morbum mentis,</hi> I think, ſaith he, it is ſcarce poſſible for any man to put an exact difference between the biting of the Serpent, and the concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence and pravity of the mind. So again in the ſame place, <hi>Non accepi fateor, unde aſsignem certam notionem inter partum cordis, &amp; ſeminarium hoſtis.</hi> I have nor, ſaith he, attained to aſſign any diſtinction between the Birth the heart travels with, and the evil Tares the Enemy ſows and caſts in; it is moſt uncertain what I ſhould attribute to my ſelf, what to him. Now if
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:62133:37"/> Satan can thus caſt in ſuggeſtions, in ſuch an inſenſible manner, he muſt needs gain an advantage, becauſe this way the gates of the ſoul are more readily opened to him. If men did apprehend ſuch and ſuch ſuggeſtions came immediately from the Devil, they would abhor to yield or hearken to them.</p>
                  <p>But when they apprehend them to be nothing but motions, and deſires ariſing in themſelves, they are more apt to entertain a parly, and to comply with them. If <hi>Peter,</hi> when he tempted Chriſt <hi>to ſpare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, Mat.</hi> 16. 22. had conceived it had been from the Devil, certainly he would never have ſaid it; but he looked upon it only as the ſtirring of his own affection. If <hi>David</hi> had thought, that the provocation to number the People had ſprang from Satan, he would not have been ſo earneſt in it. But that which makes this Wile of Satan more dangerous, is, that though he have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times circumvented us in this kind, yet we know not how to beware of him. If one through ſhew of Friendſhip, or through ſlattery hath been injurious to us, we can ever after beware of him, and not admic him to counſel us; but here it is otherwiſe. When Satan hath come to day, and deceived us in this kind, he may come again to morrow, and do it, becauſe we cannot diſcern between his ſuggeſtions, and our own thoughts. Yet we may ſuſpect them, when we find that they are (1.) Againſt nature, ſuch where the very ſhadow of a thought peeping out ſtrikes the fleſh into a trembling. (2.) When ſudden and violent like lightning. (3.) When without reaſonings, being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with importunity.</p>
                  <p>But the beſt remedy againſt this Wile is not to be curious in the ſearch to diſtinguiſh between his ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and our concupiſcence, but to be careful not to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:62133:38"/> conſent, and to remember <hi>Omnis mali cogitatio, eſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiqui ſerpentis caput,</hi> (as <hi>Pariſienſis</hi> out of <hi>Jerom</hi> ſpeaks,) that evil thoughts are the head of the old Serpent.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IX.</head>
                  <p>THe ninth Wile, which is a very great ſubtilty and device of Satan, <hi>is in his deluſions about Doctrine, in ſeducing and drawing men a ſide into errour by plauſible Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and Doctrines, that ſeem to come near the Scripture in ſhew,</hi> and being like unto it as Alchymy is like Gold. Such are, as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſaith of the <hi>Cantharides, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricolores,</hi> but they ſpit poyſon <hi>venenum ejaculantur.</hi> A pregnant inſtance of this we have, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 1, 2. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 7. Some falſe Teachers (for Satan hath his Apoſtles and Miniſters as well as Chriſt) came with the plauſible Doctrine of Mortification; For what could tend more to Mortification than the thoughts of the nearneſs of the Day of Judgment; and to ſtrengthen this opinion, they pretend they came to the knowledge of this truth, partly by Revelation from the Spirit, partly by computing the Years, and partly by ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the Apoſtles had written. Now, what was there in this opinion that was hurtful? Two things may be ſaid for it, (1.) That it is an opinion that comes very near the Scripture; doth not <hi>Peter</hi> ſay almoſt the ſame thing, <hi>Be ſober and watch, the end of all things is at hand,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Nay, doth not <hi>Paul</hi> ſay the very ſelf-ſamething, 1 <hi>Cor. 10. 11. The ends of the World are come.</hi> (2.) It tends much to Mortification, and the practice of holineſs, Do you think men would not live holily if they did apprehend the Day of Judgment near, that it would be ſhortly? Would not this keep
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:62133:38"/> down abundance of corruption? How doth <hi>Jerom profeſs himſelf overawed with this, that he thought he heard the ſound of the last Trumpet whatſoever he was a doing?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to diſcover this Wile, let me again tell you two things: (1.) Wherein it differs from the Scripture. (2.) To ſhew the danger of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> It differs from Scripture thus, the word <hi>Peter</hi> uſes is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>appropinquat,</hi> approaches; and ſo <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>the ends of the world are coming.</hi> But the word <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſes their opinion by is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>inſtat,</hi> it ſhall be upon them living, <hi>hoc anno,</hi> as <hi>Grotius</hi> ſaith, this year; and ſo the word is in other places uſed for things preſent, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 22. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>all are yours, things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, Rom.</hi> 8. 38. Now they ſaid the day of the Lord is upon us; it is a word, as <hi>Grotius</hi> ſaith, noting proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, nearneſs. So that their drift was to bring the day of the Lord within ſuch a ſmall ſpace, as within a year or few months.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Wherein lay the danger of it, what got Satan by it? To ſhew the hurt of this opinion, he might aime at three things by it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It might occaſion liberty in ſin, ſome might rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as they 1 <hi>Cor. 15. 13. Let us eat and drink, for to morrow we ſhall dye.</hi> The rage of wicked and ungodly men might put them into exceſs of riot, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 12. Satan himſelf hath great rage, knowing his time is but ſhort: and ſo wicked men, when they know their time is but ſhort, that they have but a little ſpace to take their fill of ſin in, they might be brought to a greater animoſity againſt what was good, and to a greater ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in all that was evil.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It might work a great deal of conſternation, and dejection in weak Chriſtians, whom the very thoughts
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:62133:39"/> of ſo great and ſad a day approaching might either with trembling, or fear, or many jealouſies over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The main end was this, to weaken the authority of Scripture; admit but a lye in Scripture, and all its Authority will fall to the ground. Let it be once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained or taught by Scripture or divine Revelation, that Chriſt ſhall come at ſuch a time, and this time not anſwering, now faith comes to be weakened; as the delay of Chriſts coming bred ſcoffing in ſome, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 4. and made others ſay, <hi>there is no Reſurrection,</hi> or that it <hi>is paſt already.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And thus <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> in his 80 Ep. writing to <hi>Heſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius,</hi> that was troubled in this kind, and apt to think the day of judgment might be ſuch a time, thus advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes him, to beware how he leaned to ſuch opinions, reproaches and inſultations of enemies, <hi>Multos infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos a Chriſtianâ fide avertentium, dicendo tam fallacitèr regnum eſſe promiſsum, quam fallacitèr dicebatur cito eſſe venturum.</hi> That many weak ones would be drawn by them from the Chriſtian Faith; and they would ſay there was no more certainty in the thing it ſelf than in the Prediction, that it ſhould be ſo ſuddenly; And he adds, <hi>Qui dicit dominum citius eſse venturum optabilius loquitur ſed periculoſius fallitur.</hi> The Doctrine of Chriſts ſpeedy coming is more deſirable, but the miſtake is more dangerous. So that the danger is in this, a man may call in queſtion many other truths, as well as them which before he thought he did believe. Therefore let me ſpeak to you that are Chriſtians, do not think thoſe Doctrines that ſeem to come near, and be like the Scripture, may preſently be entertained, or hearkened to, but be ſure that they come up to the Scripture, and be adaequate to the Rule, if not, they are in no wiſe to be hearkened unto.</p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:62133:39"/>
                  <p>O that we had in this kind the Zeal and Affection of our Fore-fathers, who did contend for the truth, that they would not loſe an Iota, one tittle of it. The Council of <hi>Nice</hi> would not gratifie <hi>Arrius</hi> in a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, he would grant Chriſt was of a like, not of the ſame ſubſtance. By the ſound he ſeemed to come near the truth. But as two men upon the top of two Mountains ſeem ſo near they can ſhake hands, but muſt go a great way before they meet. So it is here, they ſeem near the truth in words, but were a great way off it. And ſo the <hi>Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> in acknowledging the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a letter only changed, but made a wide diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; and ſo the Latine and Greek Church, in the proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt, differed in a Prepoſition. The Greek would grant the Holy Ghoſt to proceed by the Son <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; and ſo for the <hi>filioque added to the Nicene Creed.</hi> Truth muſt not be loſt by things that come near it; if any Doctrine come not up to the Scriptures, it muſt be rejected. If it go beyond them, it is ſtraw and ſtubble on the foundation. If it fall ſhort, it is errour alſo. Remember that corrupt opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, like Changelings, are many times laid in the place of the right Child, which is Truth. <hi>O fooliſh Galatians,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>who hath bewitched you that you ſhould not obey the truth?</hi> a Metaphor taken from thoſe that uſe Witchery, and preſent falſe ſhapes to the eyes, as the Witch of <hi>Eudor</hi> did the likeneſs of <hi>Samuel</hi> to <hi>Saul;</hi> but remember this is a Wile of Satan, who him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf abode not in the truth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. 44. Labour to have the Signature of all Divine Truths imprinted on your minds. <hi>Veritas animae pabulum,</hi> as <hi>Lactantius</hi> cals it, Truth is the food of the ſoul. It is <hi>Sponſa humani intellectus, ex eâ generat ſobolem,</hi> as <hi>Pariſienſis,</hi> the Spouſe of the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:62133:40"/> Underſtanding, by which it hath iſſue. It is a part of that Armour the Apoſtle calls <hi>Armour of light.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe then much with God the Father of Lights, <hi>James</hi> 1. 17. with the Word, which is a Book of light; with the Saints, the Children of light, if you would eſcape this Wile.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. X.</head>
                  <p>THe tenth Subtilty of Satan when theſe things will not do, then <hi>under pretence of ſetting up the Spirit, and Revelations, he labours to cry down the Word of God, and all the ordinary Miniſterial Officers Chriſt hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his Church,</hi> and all Doctrines and Explications of Scripture are caſhiered and rejected. Theſe are <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Our firſt worthy reformers found a bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conflict herein: For they no ſooner had prevailed to reſtore the Goſpel, and expel the darkneſs of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in <hi>Germany,</hi> and other parts, but ſtraitway Satan ſows his Tares; they called thoſe that adhered to the Scriptures, <hi>Vocaliſtae, Literaliſtae,</hi> Vocaliſts, Literaliſts; and hereby they made the work of Reformation odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as <hi>Eli</hi> his Sons made the Sacrifices of the Lord to be abhorred. And as in Superſtitious times he kept down the truth by Superſtition, and pompous Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, ſo in times of Reformation by pretended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations, and Teachings above the Word. And this the Apoſtle doth much aim at when he ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor. 11. 14. That Satan transforms himſelf into an Angel of light.</hi> This deluſion I ſpeak the rather of, becauſe that in theſe times wherein Reformation hath been much pretended, the World by pretences of Revelations, and impulſes of the Spirit, hath caſt off the Word. This Art he improves two waies:</p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:62133:40"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Some are meer pretences, when wicked and wretched miſcreants do on purpoſe, and knowingly uſe this way as a pretence to colour all their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Thus <hi>Mahomet,</hi> to colour his wickedneſs in the ſeducing the people, pretended the fits of the Falling ſickneſs he was troubled with to be certain Ecſtacies and Raviſhments, at the appearance of the <hi>Angel Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briel,</hi> and the Dove picking the Corn out of his Ear to be the appearance of the Holy Ghoſt. And thus often times thoſe who uſe ſuch curſed pretences come to be admired, and eſteemed, who elſe would have been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted as nought. As <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaks of two Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, <hi>Primianus,</hi> and <hi>Maximianus,</hi> that if they had not taken that way, <hi>Primianus</hi> might have been <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtremianus,</hi> and <hi>Maximianus</hi> might have been <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miamus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> He improves this ſubtilty by deluding the fancies of men with a concurrence of pride, and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admiration, ſo as to entertain thoughts that none know ſo much of God, nor have ſuch ſecret Communion with him as they, and that thereby they have ſundry particulars above all the world revealed to them. Thus ſome have magnified themſelves in particulars, that have been revealed to them, that have come to paſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Acoſta</hi> the Jeſuite tells us of one that was a very great Schollar, that through deluſions and fancies fell into ſuch a conceit, as he believed he had holineſs gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto him above Angels, and that he was the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the world in regard of efficacy, and Chriſt in regard of ſufficiency; that he had the Hypoſtatical Union offered to him, and that he did refuſe it. Thus Satan puffs men up with pride, that he may make them inſtruments of confuſion and ruine to the Church.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:62133:41"/> Therefore as an Antidote againſt this keep to the Word, 2 <hi>Pet. 1. 19. You have a more ſure word of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy.</hi> Notwithſtanding all Satans Stratagems to adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate it by Hereticks, to deſtroy it by Tyrants, to debaſe it by prophane ſcoffing at it, yet hold to the Word, <hi>ad Legem, &amp; teſtimonium,</hi> if they ſpeak not according to them, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. XI.</head>
                  <p>THe eleventh Wile, by which Satan winneth and allureth many to the hazard and peril of their Eternal welfare, <hi>is by the working many lying Signs, and Wonders, and Miracles.</hi> That look as God, for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of his Goſpel, did at the firſt publiſhing it confirm it with <hi>many Miracles, and Wonders,</hi> Heb. 2. 4. So Satan, for the facilitating a belief the better to his lyes, and falſhood, doth put forth much of his power in the working of lying ſigns and miracles. This the Scripture often expreſſes as a policy above all he almoſt uſeth, <hi>Mat. 24. 24. For there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets, and ſhew many ſigns and wonders. Rev. 13. 13. 2 Theſ.</hi> 2. 9. Where the coming of that man of ſin is deſcribed to be <hi>after the working of Satan,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>with all power, and ſigns, and lying wonders.</hi> Which words do imply, as I conceive, both the manner, &amp; means of Antichriſts working. (1.) The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Antichriſts working is after the way and manner of Satans working; that is, it holds proportion unto that way that he uſeth to take. (2.) It is by the means of Satan; he as a faſt friend of Antichriſt puts out his power in his behalf for the working many lying ſigns and wonders: which are called lying ſigns and wonders in two reſpects: (1.) In regard of their
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:62133:41"/> formality, they want that which ſhould conſtitute a true miracle. For a Miracle truly called, is the doing ſome work extraordinary that runs into the ſenſes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding the power of any Creature, as to make the Sun ſtand ſtill in the Heavens by a word, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now, all Satans workings are but ſometimes a deceiving of the ſenſe, as <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Magicians; ſometimes a deluding of the fancy; ſometimes there is an expoſing of ſecret things of nature to the ſenſe of the Ignorant, who not knowing the depths of nature, think it a wonder; ſometimes by applying of Actives to Paſſives, all which fall ſhort of Miracles. (2.) They are called lying in regard of the end of them, they tend to draw from the truth, and therefore are not to be credited, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 8.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. XII.</head>
                  <p>THe twelfth ſubtilty of Satan <hi>is to aſſault and afflict Christians with ſuch temptations as to their knowledge and experience are unheard of, which happily they never heard any others to be tempted to, nor believe that ever any but themſelves have had experience of.</hi> This <hi>Pariſienſis</hi> calls, <hi>Extraneitas tentationis,</hi> temptations that they cannot parallel or ſample. Now, when Chriſtians are exerciſed with ſuch temptations, it exceedingly ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes them, as new Engines and weapons, not before ſeen by Souldiers in former fights, do amaze the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, and take off his courage; and as new diſeaſes, of which Phyſicians have had no experience, do moſt poſe and trouble them, and oftentimes diſcourage both Patients, and Phyſicians. So oftentimes new tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions do moſt amaze and ſad the ſoul.</p>
                  <p>Hence come thoſe complaints tempted ones do ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:62133:42"/> No body was ever troubled as I am, who was ever aſſaulted with ſuch blaſphemous thoughts, ſuch Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal injections, as I dare not ſpeak or mention? Sure if I were not worſe than others, I could not have ſuch thoughts; if I were not forſaken of God, he would not ſuffer me to be thus tempted. But in this caſe you muſt remember what <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 13. <hi>There is no temptation happened to you but what is common to man;</hi> I may truly ſay to ſuch, they think it new, yet it is that which ſome Chriſtian or other have had experience of. You know what <hi>Elias</hi> ſaid to God, and what Gods anſwer was, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 3. ſaith he, <hi>I am left alone, and they ſeek my life.</hi> But what ſaith the anſwer of God unto him, <hi>I have reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to my ſelf ſeven thouſand men,</hi> &amp;c. So you think you are alone in this or that temptation, but alas there are a thouſand in the Militant Church that are affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the ſame temptations, and Stratagems of Satan.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. XIII.</head>
                  <p>THe thirteenth Wile is about holy duties, and that (1.) <hi>In putting us to do good duties upon wrong ends, which wholly alter their property.</hi> It is a true Axiom in Philoſophy, <hi>Quod forma in naturalibus, finis in mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus,</hi> What the form is in naturals, the end is in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals. In moral things the end ſpecificates the action. <hi>Jehu's</hi> ſlaying <hi>Ahabs</hi> Children, was not obedience, but murther, though done by Gods Command, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1. 4. God required it as a righteous ſatisfaction to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, but <hi>Jehu</hi> did it out of ambition, therefore God ſaith, <hi>I will avenge the bloud of Jezreel upon the houſe of Jehu.</hi> Alms are good when they come like oyl that
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:62133:42"/> makes no noiſe, but not when a Trumpet is blown before them. Prayer is good when it comes from Zeal, but it is but howling when it comes from luſt, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7. 14. Worſhipping God is good, but if it be for baſe ends it is but ſelf-ſeeking. Oh therefore look to all duties, God muſt not only be the Object, but the End; Worſhip muſt have no end below it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>Or (2.) Satans VVile is, when he cannot hinder from duty, then he endeavours to ſpoyl them; he will excite to duties, but to do them unſeaſonably. It is the commendation of a duty when it is done in ſeaſon, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. The bleſſed man <hi>brings forth his fruit in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> Now, when he cannot put out the Candle, he will make it ſparkle and flair, as in <hi>Martha, Luk.</hi> 10. 40, 41. or he will turn affection the wrong way. The Jews were zealous for the Law, and he ſtirs up that againſt the Goſpel. <hi>Saul</hi> had a conſcience of ſerving God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. 12. and he forceth him to offer Sacrifice. The <hi>Corinthians</hi> were at firſt too remiſs towards the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtuous <hi>Corinthian,</hi> after too ſevere; he ſees ſome heat, and he drives it on too much; <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he will make us tyrannize in ſome ſervice, and ſome duties he will make tyrants unto us, his aim is by marrying Religion and Tyranny to diſcourage men from Religion.</p>
                  <p>(3.) His deſign is to preſs Chriſtians with ſome violent aſſault when they are preparing themſelves for duty, or to afflict them ſo in the duty, that it may be rather their work to keep off the fowls from the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, than to give up themſelves to God in the duty as they ſhould do. Therefore he preſſes Chriſtians with extraordinary diſcouragements when they are to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form extraordinary duty, that if he cannot keep them from ordinary, he may keep them from extraordinary duties, and labours to make them ſo uncomfortable,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:62133:43"/> as many are afraid to perform them. Thus many are kept month after month, and year after year, from ever medling with the Sacrament (who will pray and hear,) through the violent aſſaults of Satan, ſo that ſome have given over duties for a kind of eaſe, rather than be ſo aſſaulted. All I ſhall ſay to this is, whatever your diſcouragements are give not over.</p>
                  <p>Satan may imbitter a ſweet duty by his temptations, but he ſhall not make it ineffectual; while you are wraſtling and ſtriving, his deſign is but by this violence to make you give over, to chooſe rather to walk in a kind of peace, than to maintain a war in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of duty.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. XIV.</head>
                  <p>THe fourteenth Wile is <hi>by ſuffering falſe remedies to prevail.</hi> The Devil ſuggeſts theſe to keep men from the true, and tells men, as <hi>Samſon</hi> did <hi>Dalilah,</hi> if he be ſo and ſo uſed he ſhall be overcome. Thus the Jews uſed their <hi>Phylacteries,</hi> as <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, remedies againſt inchantments. And thoſe two Commandments upon which Chriſt ſaies hang the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, the Chriſtians did, from the ſuperſtitious Jews, write them in Schedules, and hang them about their necks, as little Goſpels; but thoſe were <hi>portanda in corde, non in corpore,</hi> as <hi>Jerom</hi> ſaith well upon <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. they were to be laid up in the heart, not to be worn about the body. So the Papiſts uſe Salt, Spittle, holy Water in their Exorciſms, but theſe the Devil, that helliſh Leviathan, eſteemeth leſs than the Leviathan, in <hi>Job</hi> 41. 27. doth of Iron, which he eſteemeth as ſtraw, and of Braſs as rotten wood. Beware then of his counterfeit weapons; think not theſe things will
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:62133:43"/> affright the Devil, rather look up to God, as <hi>David,</hi> who praies, <hi>that God would turn the counſel of Achitophel to fooliſhneſs,</hi> 2 Sam. 15. 31.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. XV.</head>
                  <p>THe fifteenth Wile, <hi>is by making falſe Syllogiſms, by which he works upon the guilt of conſcience,</hi> and this conſiſts in laying to our charge ſins of omiſſion or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, in which the Major or Minor is falſe. As now he will lay to our charge many particular ſins and corruptions committed by us, as pride, hypocriſie, ſelf-reſpects, and ſo many duties omitted, or done overly. Which temptation if drawn in a Syllogiſm, either the firſt or ſecond propoſition is falſe.</p>
                  <p>He in whom ſuch ſin raigns as hypocriſie is, is not the Child of God. But ſuch a one art thou, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Minor here many times is falſe. It is true, a Child of God cannot be an hypocrite, but he may have hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie in him; the beſt way therefore to reſiſt this temptation, is to try whether hypocriſie reign in thee, and this he will preſs by aggravating the evil, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuating the good, that he may bring men into trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Sometime by making falſe Majors, as that to relapſe into the ſame ſin is not compatible with grace, and for the trial he gives falſe rules and ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dards to judge by. Thus he troubles weak Chriſtians, about their graces and comforts, by falſe Syllogiſms. He aggravates their imperfections in the former, tells them what falls they catch when they would run; what diſtractions they meet with when they moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend their minds, and how can Gods Eye, that is pure, behold theſe things with delight? Now to diſcover the fallacy of this Argument: You muſt know, that as we
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:62133:44"/> are not to place the ſtrength of our confidence in our own righteouſneſs, as if it would abide the ſeverity of Gods trial, <hi>For how can man be juſtified with God, Job</hi> 25. 4. So the perfection of our righteouſneſs is not to be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the perfectneſs of the work, but by the upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the will, and ſincerity of the endeavour aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring towards perfection. Every failing doth not make a man an hypocrite. <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> had many failings, he made a League of amity with <hi>Ahab, 2 Chron.</hi> 18. 3. He went to <hi>Ramoth Gilead</hi> with him, notwithſtanding <hi>Micaiahs</hi> Propheſie againſt it, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18. 27, 28. Though re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by <hi>Jehu</hi> the Prophet he joyns in a ſpecial League with <hi>Ahaziah, Ahabs</hi> Son, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. 35. He beſtows his Son upon <hi>Ahabs</hi> Daughter, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21. 6. Yet God reckons him a holy man, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22. 43. It is ſaid, <hi>He turned not aſide from that which was right in the ſight of the Lord.</hi> If therefore obedience be interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, caſt not away your confidence. <hi>If any man ſin we have an Advocate with the Father.</hi> You have to do with a God, that will make thy works at laſt more than at firſt. So in point of comfort he argues: If thou hadſt faith thou wouldſt have joy and peace; but thou haſt no joy, therefore no faith; for 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 8. <hi>Believing ye rejoyce.</hi> Now to anſwer this we are to know, that Faith is the root upon which all true joy grows, it is the flower whereof that is the ſtalk, but it is not alwaies to be found flouriſhing upon it. There are three ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons when joy is moſt eminent, and when God doth moſt abundantly diſpence it.</p>
                  <p n="1">(1.) In young Chriſtians, in Lambs whom he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in his boſome, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40 11. With joy and comfort that they may be ſtrengthened. God would not carry <hi>Iſrael</hi> by the way of the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> Exod. 13. 17. <hi>Leſt the people ſee war, and repent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:62133:44"/>(2.) After great ſtorms God makes broken bones to rejoyce, <hi>Pſal. 51. 8. Make me to hear joy and gladneſs, that the bones thou haſt broken may rejoyce.</hi> After ſtorms come the greateſt calms; after his Children have been in the Depths, the greateſt Exalrations.</p>
                  <p n="3">(3.) When God calls men to witneſs his truth, <hi>Acts</hi> 27. 23. When <hi>Paul</hi> was to appear before <hi>Caeſar,</hi> God ſends an Angel to comfort him. We muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, there may be the root when there is not the fruit; that which Faith is to look at, is what the Goſpel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veals. Now the Goſpel doth not reveal that we ſhall have no ſorrow or trouble, but that the <hi>Covenant of peace ſhall not be removed from us,</hi> Iſa. 54. 10.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. XVI.</head>
                  <p>THe ſixteenth Wile <hi>is to perſwade Chriſtians whom he doth thus afflict to keep his counſel, ſo as either through ſhame or fear they dare ſay nothing,</hi> like men that have foul diſeaſes, had rather dye than tell the Phyſician. Like the <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> Boy, that ſuffered the Fox to eat out his bowels, and would not reveale it; So many ſuffer temptations to eat out their hearts. Thus Satan wounds, and would not have Chriſtians complain; he tempts, and ſollicites, and would not have Chriſtians to ask counſel, and ſo many times the burden falls the heavier, and the wound ſmarts the more. Whereas if experienced Chriſtians were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with them it might be a help to them; as Wind ſtifled in the bowels of the Earth ſhakes it, but finding paſſage does no harm; ſo oftentimes the very opening the Devils temptations is enough to ſcatter them. We ſhould therefore ſeek for remedy, by communicating our grief to wiſe Chriſtians, that will
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:62133:45"/> pray for us, and not deride us; and not gratifie ſin in that it loves ſo well, <hi>viz.</hi> to be concealed and hid.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. XVII.</head>
                  <p>THe ſeventeenth Wile, is to <hi>aſſault us in ſuch tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations wherein we leaſt ſuſpect our ſelves,</hi> and to which happily neither conſtitution, nor any cuſtome of ours carries us, but only the preſent occaſion draws forth our corruption. Thus men that are many times by nature patient, and exceeding pittiful, yet ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſported into a paſſion, become cruel. Thus <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperour, upon a meer paſſion, one of his Souldiers ſuffering an injury, put to death at <hi>leaſt three thouſand in Theſſalonica.</hi> Some of the Ancients are of opinion, that the Devil ſtirred up the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to make the Golden Calf that he might put <hi>Moſes</hi> in a heat, who was the meekeſt man, that ſo he might break the Tables of the Law, and might not reprove their ſin. Therefore ſuſpect your ſelves prone to every ſin, do not repoſe any thing upon Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. XVIII.</head>
                  <p>THe eighteenth Wile, <hi>Hopes of returning out of ſin by a ſpeedy repentance, and a timely revocation.</hi> But where is the promiſe of return? Are there not rather dreadful threatnings, of permitting ſuch to go on to final Apoſtacy? It is eaſie to throw thy ſelf head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long from the Pinnacle of the Temple, but thou cauſt not ſtay thy ſelf from falling without a Miracle; Our hearts are like Spring-Locks, will ſhut of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:62133:45"/> but will not open without a Key. <hi>Non eſt laus ſtetiſſe in pinaculo, ſed ſtetiſſe, &amp; non cecidiſſe,</hi> as <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> ſaies: It is is no commendation to ſtand on the Pinacle, but to keep out ſtanding, and not to fall, when we are in ſuch danger.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. XIX.</head>
                  <p>THe nineteenth Wile, <hi>to keep raw, and ſmarting, any wounds, that the Spirit hath inflicted upon the conſcience of any poor ſoul.</hi> True it is, Satan is not able to afflict immediately and really the conſcience of a man, no more than he is able to comfort a mans conſcience; as it is Gods Prerogative to know the heart, ſo it is to afflict and comfort the heart. But yet Satan may help to keep the wounds raw, by diſturbing the fancy, and filling them with horrour, and terrour; he may ſhake and rattle the Chains, though he cannot put them on upon any poor ſoul, and thereby keep them from comfort which is their portion; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when terrours ſo affright, as to the prejudice of all medicines, we may ſuſpect the hand of Satan in them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. XX.</head>
                  <p>THe twentieth VVile <hi>is to draw aſide the ſoul to ſome ſin when it is in the purſuit of ſome great mercy, or neer the enjoyment of it,</hi> that ſo either their hands may be weakned in the purſuit, and give over through the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of their own guilt, which alwaies weakens confidence, or elſe may help to ſpoyl the ſweetneſs of it in the enjoyment. Thus when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was nigh the enjoying of a great bleſſing, the Land that God had promiſed: Upon the borders they fall a murmuring,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:62133:46"/> by their hearkening to the Spies, who had brought an evil report upon the Land, <hi>Num.</hi> 13. 32, 33. <hi>It is a Land that eateth up the Inhabitants, and the people that we ſaw in it were men of a great ſtature, and there we ſaw the Giants,</hi> &amp;c. So that hereby they neglected the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and let the mercy at a low rate. So that thoſe that are beggars, and expectants of any great mercy, had need to be watchers too.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. XXI.</head>
                  <p>THe one and twentieth VVile, <hi>to make the duties of a Chriſtians general and particular calling interfere and claſh one with another.</hi> There is a double calling in which every man is ſet: There is <hi>Vocatio ad faedus, &amp; vocatio ad munus;</hi> or as we uſe to ſpeak, a general, and a particular calling, it is termed our <hi>general calling,</hi> not only for its extent, but becauſe the things we are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to are but one and the ſame, and common to all; we are called to the ſame duties, to the ſame promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to the ſame profeſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The particular calling is that in which men are not called to one and the ſame duty, but do act according to ſeveral gifts, one in this employment, another in that. Now both theſe are to be performed regularly, and this is the excellency of a Chriſtian when he ſo orders his particular calling, that it doth not eat up the time that is due to his general calling, and when he ſo orders his general calling, as that it doth not take away the time that God hath allotted for his particular calling; now Satans great Art is to diſturb Chriſtians in the performance of theſe. Some therefore are never quiet, but when they are hearing, praying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but their particular callings and relations they never mind; this is Satans deſign to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:62133:46"/> diſturb them by putting them upon prayer, when di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence is required in their particular calling. O<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs he takes off from hearing, and praying, and thoſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which belong to Chriſtians, as ſuch, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence they muſt provide for their Families; that ſo while they care for their bodies, they may altogether neglect the care of the inward man. Therefore know it is a great part of a Chriſtians prudence, and that which affords a great deal of comfort, duly to manage both callings, when you do not let the time of your callings devour the time of your duties, but let your ſoul have its portion of your time as well as your body. Separate then your ſouls for a ſeaſon to go up in the Mount, and converſe with God, that you may be more ſit when you come down again to converſe with men in your particular callings.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. XXII.</head>
                  <p>THe two and twentieth, and laſt Wile, <hi>is that which the Text hints, an endeavour of Satan to bring us from one extream to another, that we may be kept from the golden mean,</hi> wherein Grace ſtan<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s as well as Vertue, which you know is ſeated between two Vices, as <hi>Solomons</hi> Throne was between two rows of Lions. And this device he uſes in matters of ſin, in matters of duty, and in matters of Doctrine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In matters of ſin.</hi> Thus the inceſtuous <hi>Corinthian,</hi> is firſt puffed up with pride, and ſins preſumptuouſly, and then when by the Cenſures of the Church he is awakened to ſee his ſin, then he is well nigh ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up with ſorrow.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In religious duties,</hi> firſt he tempts to a neglect of them, or ſuch a rigorous tyranny, that makes many to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:62133:47"/> groan under them, and lye under woful ſnares. And this device he accounts the more prevalent, becauſe we are apt to think oft times that the very work of grace lies in the higheſt oppoſition to that ſin or vice that ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth heavieſt upon our hearts, when as indeed ſins and vices are not only oppoſite to vertues, but one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, be ſure therefore remember grace lies in a mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle way. Sorrow for ſin is not deſperation, confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in God is not preſumption, but the middle way, Faith leaves both extreams, and cloſes with God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rule of the Word.</p>
                  <p>So again <hi>in matters of Doctrine. Baſil</hi> writing againſt <hi>Sabellius</hi> to overthrow his Haereſie, uttered ſome incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient expreſſions about the Trinity. And <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> in his zeal againſt the <hi>Pelagians</hi> who ſlighted Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, was carried out ſo that he became <hi>durus pater infantum,</hi> pronouncing thoſe dying unbaptized not to be ſaved. But I ſhall not inſiſt any longer upon that ſecond general, the enumeration of Satans VViles.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein are laid down ſeveral Antidotes againſt the Wiles of Satan.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe next thing is to lay down ſome Scripture Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes and preſervatives againſt them. That may keep you, not from being tempted by Satan, but from being touched by the evil one, as St. <hi>John</hi> phraſeth it, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 17. That the evil one touch you not, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it is the ſame word uſed 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 1. The
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:62133:47"/> evil one doth not touch him ſo as to produce his own Image and likeneſs upon him. Though I undertake not ſuch Antidotes and preſervatives as ſhall totally free you from his Wiles, yet I ſhall lay down Antidotes againſt his poyſon. Such premonitions againſt his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties, ſuch Scripture Armour againſt his rage and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, as will, if uſed, keep you from being overcome by him.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>CHriſtian Sobriety and Watchfulneſs. This we have from the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 Pet. 5. 8. <hi>Be ſober, be vigilant, becauſe your adverſary the devil goeth about like a roaring Lion,</hi> &amp;c. Sobriety ſtands in a moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards the things of this life. Pleaſures, Riches, Honours, they are the uſual baits with which Satan hides all his hooks, and temptations, that ſo they may not be eaſily diſcerned, and an immoderate thirſting, a keen eager appetite after theſe things, is the ready way to bring a Believer into the midſt of ſnares. <hi>They that will be rich,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 9. whoſe deſires and appetites are filled with the great things of the world, <hi>fall into many ſnares:</hi> Sometimes to ſtrain their conſciences by deceit; ſometimes to do evil acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it may be to make the ſtream of their actions great by the bloud of others. But now as we muſt be ſober in tempering our hearts, and affections, ſo we muſt be watchful, which is a duty required of us as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, but indiſpenſably neceſſary as we are Chriſtian Souldiers, engaged <hi>in bello ſemper, et ſi non in praelio,</hi> as <hi>Livy</hi> ſpeaks, alwaies in a War, though not alwaies in battel; a Chriſtian hath no peace but in his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and the grave. Nay, it is an irreconcileable Controverſie, it is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Venenata non fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:62133:48"/> inducias,</hi> a war without a truce. Therefore a Chriſtians life is c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lled a Warfare; they are trained up <hi>non in deliciis, ſed in caſtris;</hi> not in the pleaſures of a Court, but the hardineſs of a Camp. Chriſt, who is their he<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, is therefore called in Scripture, <hi>a man of war, Exod. 15. 3. A Leader,</hi> and <hi>Commander</hi> to the People, <hi>Iſa. 55. 4. A Captain, Heb.</hi> 2. 10. And Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who are his Members, <hi>Souldiers, 2 Tim. 2. 3. Thou therefore as a good ſouldier of Jeſus Chriſt endure hardſhip;</hi> their courſe of life, <hi>a fight, 1 lim.</hi> 4. 8. They which oppoſe them, <hi>enemies, Luk.</hi> 1. 71. Their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, <hi>aſſaults, 1 Pet.</hi> 2. 11. This, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, is confirmed by the authority of God himſelf, <hi>Gen. 3. 15. I will put enmity between thy ſeed and the ſeed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</hi> Therefore we muſt carry our ſelves as Souldiers, and maintain our watch. Now, though watching in the firſt ſignification doth relate to the body, and doth imply more than to awake from ſleep, for it is <hi>Cautae attenti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, quâ res aliqua diligenter curatur;</hi> it is a heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful care and obſerving any thing we deſire to keep ſafe; yet in a metaphorical ſenſe it is applyed to the mind, and ſo it is a circumſpect, and wiſe care in obſerving the frame and deportment of the whole ſoul. It is (1.) a circumſpect care, ſo thoſe two words the Apoſtle uſeth a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> prayer do import, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 18. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which ſignifies ſuch a watching as not to lay the eyes together, of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>minimum quid, ſic gry apud Latinos,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>ſomnus,</hi> it notes not the leaſt tendency to ſleep. It is a Military kind of Speech, ſaith <hi>Grotius,</hi> from the watchings in war, which are uſually moſt ſtrict. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther word is <hi>Col.</hi> 4. 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which <hi>Euſtachius</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>ſuſci<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o,</hi> ſuch a watching wherein men do ſtir and rouze up themſelves. (2.) It is a wiſe care; watching is nothing elſe but the exerciſe of prudence.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:62133:48"/> (3.) It muſt be of the whole ſoul, every faculty muſt be obſerved; as at every Avennue there is a Sentinel, ſo on every Faculty there muſt be a watch. And have not we need thus to watch againſt ſin, and unto duty? Shall Satan be watchful, and we be drowſie? Shall <hi>he continually go about ſeeking whom he may devour,</hi> and ſhall not we be circumſpect to conſider how we may deliver our ſelves out of his paws? It was certainly an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiding to the Diſciples, <hi>Mar. 14. 33. Simon, ſleepeſt thou? Could you not watch one hour? Judas non dormit, Judas</hi> doth not ſleep: They were not ſo diligent to ſave their Maſter, as <hi>Judas</hi> was to betray him. And is it not a great reproach to a Chriſtian, that he is not ſo watchful to ſave himſelf, as the Devil is to deſtroy him? Exerciſe watchfulneſs over your corrupt natures; the devil may tempt us, but he cannot hurt us without our conſent; he hath <hi>aſtutiam ſuadendi non potentiam cogendi;</hi> he may perſwade, but he cannot compel: our Corrupt nature is the tinder upon which Satan ſtrikes all his ſparks; as Birdlime is made of the dung of birds, ſo Satans ſnares are made out of the diſpoſitions that are in the heart to ſin. The <hi>Alchymists</hi> that boaſt of turning Iron into Silver, Copper into Braſs, aſſign the ground from the ſubalternation of Mettals, that there is a diſpoſition in thoſe Mettals to receive the <hi>Perfectum</hi> of the other. So Satan forms his tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, upon our innate diſpoſition, he draws out into act thoſe latent diſpoſitions in us. (2.) Watch over the <hi>Peccatum in deliciis,</hi> over the maſter ſin, the boſome ſin, watch ſtrictly over this.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>THe ſecond Antidote <hi>is Reſolution and Chriſti<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> courage;</hi> This is as neceſſary as watchfulneſs.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:62133:49"/> Watchfulneſs is good to prevent evil, and Chriſtian Reſolution to undergo it. And we have need of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, for he that will be a Chriſtian muſt expect oppoſition; we muſt not think to paſs out of <hi>Aegypt</hi> without <hi>Pharaohs</hi> purſuing us: Or to travel through the wilderneſs of this world without oppoſition from theſe <hi>Amalekites.</hi> Satan will be in arms againſt us if he perceive but thoughts of our departure. If once we be but big with any holy reſolutions, he will perſecute us, as he did the woman in <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. Therefore be reſolute. This the Apoſtle exhorts to, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 10. <hi>Finally Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might, put on the whole Armour of God.</hi> Why? <hi>That you may be able to ſtand againſt the Wiles of the devil.</hi> Take up reſolution in the name of Chriſt to hold out, <hi>Judg.</hi> 20. 22. The men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> encouraged themſelves, and ſet the Battel <hi>again</hi> in array. <hi>Libentius te inſequitur ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſarius fugientem, quam ſuſtineat repugnantem, &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacius inſiſt it a tergo quam reſiſtat in faciem,</hi> as <hi>Bernard,</hi> He doth more willingly purſue than fight, and he is more bold when we turn our backs, than when we ſet our faces againſt him: Courage and conſtancy will bring victory. If you reſiſt, you overcome; he may perſwade, but cannot force. It was all <hi>Eve</hi> complained of, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 13. that the Serpent deceived her, not that he conſtrained her; and therefore he choſe the Serpent, <hi>Non quia fortior, ſed quia callidior,</hi> not becauſe he was the ſtrongeſt beaſt in the field, but becauſe he was more ſubtil. To encourage our ſelves, conſider we have a better Captain, better Armour: He fights with fleſhy weapons, <hi>but the weapons of our warfare are not carnal, but mighty through God.</hi> Our own reſolution is nothing without God. Satan knows there is nothing
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:62133:49"/> ſo mutable as man, it is proper to him, as immutability is to God. And laſtly, we have a better reward.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>THe third <hi>Antidote, in reſiſting the Wiles of Satan, make uſe of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and that in two particulars: Firſt, As a pattern to know how to reſiſt temptations. And ſecondly as an aide and ſuccour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> In reſiſting temptations, make <hi>uſe of Chriſt as a pattern,</hi> who did combate with Satan to teach us to combate. The firſt promiſe God made to fallen man was, <hi>That the ſeed of the woman ſhould bruiſe the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head,</hi> Gen. 3. 15. And the firſt work Chriſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook after his ſolemn inauguration into his Office was to fulfill this promiſe, as we ſee in <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring the field, and coping with him and all the powers of darkneſs in a ſingle duel. Now, as <hi>Abimeleck</hi> ſaid to his followers, <hi>Judg.</hi> 9. 48. <hi>What you have ſeen me do, that do you.</hi> So Chriſt our Captain bids us look unto him, and obſerve him in theſe four particulars:</p>
                  <p>1. Obſerve the weapon Chriſt choſe to foyl him by, and to reſiſt all the temptations of Satan withal; he could by his power have rebuked and ſilenced him, as eaſily as he did the winds and waves, but he doth it <hi>by the Word;</hi> and to variety of temptations he uſeth but one weapon, <hi>the Word.</hi> Againſt temptations to diſtruſt, againſt temptations to preſumption, to blaſphemy, ſaith Chriſt, it is <hi>written, man liveth not by bread. And again it is written, Thou ſhalt not tempt,</hi> &amp;c. Now in this let Chriſtians take Chriſt as an Example to reſiſt Satans ſuggeſtions by the Word; take your Arrows from that Quiver, your advice from that unerring Oracle, <hi>I have hid thy word in my heart that I might not ſin againſt thee,</hi>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:62133:50"/> Pſal. 119. The Word both <hi>diſcovers</hi> Wiles, and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifies againſt them.</hi> It firſt diſcovers all the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Satan, it is a Chryſtal Glaſs in which you may ſee all the turnings and windings of this old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. <hi>Bernard</hi> compares Chriſtians, that are diligent in the Word, unto thoſe Doves, in <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. 12. that ſit by the waters, becauſe they can in them the better diſcern the motion of the Hawk in the Heavens: So the Word diſcovers the ſnares of Satan. When <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were not careful to ask counſel of God, they were caught by the policy and craft of the <hi>Gibeonites:</hi> So when you neglect to conſult with God and his Word, no wonder if the policy of Satan pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail againſt you, <hi>Jer.</hi> 8. 9. <hi>They have rejected the word of the Lord, and what wiſdom is in them?</hi> Secondly, It for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifies againſt the Wiles of Satan, and furniſhes with many weapons and Arguments againſt them. If he promiſe great things, and ſo would ſeduce you that way, look into the Word, and there are better things than he can promiſe. For Satan can promiſe nothing, but either thou haſt it already, (and the ſame water is ſweeter from the Fountain than when it paſſes through a ſink,) or thou haſt better, thou walkeſt among fewer ſnares, thou haſt an overplus of ſpiritual goods for thy defect of earthly. Conſider, the offers of Satan are not for comforts but ſnares, not for the uſe of life, but the proviſions for ſin. If he threaten, look into the Word, there are greater and ſadder threatnings. What is his wild-fire, to fiery indignation, to ſnares, <hi>fire and brimſtone, a horrible tempeſt,</hi> that the Lord threatens to rain down upon ſinners, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11. So that in every kind you are furniſhed by the Word.</p>
                  <p>And here let me commend to you the excellency of this Weapon our Saviour made uſe of: It is called by
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:62133:50"/> the Apoſtle, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 16. <hi>The ſword of his mouth,</hi> and by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, The ſword of the Spirit.</hi> And there is no ſword like this, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid of <hi>Goliahs.</hi> All muſt give place to this. That <hi>Culter Philoſophicus,</hi> that was by a ſtrict and daily obſervation of the ſtars, made ſo as that it would cut in ſunder an Anvil; <hi>Alexanders</hi> ſword that cut the <hi>Gordian Knot; Ehuds</hi> ſword that killed <hi>Eglon</hi> King of <hi>Moab,</hi> muſt give place to this, that cuts aſunder all the gins and ſnares of Satan. The power of the VVord is ſeen in this, that though it hath all diſadvantages to hinder its operation: Yet the VVord of Gods mouth doth not return void. If applied to great perſons, it makes them tremble. <hi>Where the word of a King is there is power,</hi> Eccleſ. 8. 4. <hi>and who may ſay unto him, what dost thou?</hi> Yet with it <hi>Elijah</hi> wounds <hi>Ahab,</hi> 2 Kings 21. 19. <hi>Paul</hi> doth but brandiſh it, and <hi>Felix</hi> trembles, <hi>Felix</hi> in his Robes, <hi>Paul</hi> in his Chains. <hi>Micaiah,</hi> a Priſoner, pronounceth death to <hi>Ahab,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22. 27. The moſt ſecret ſins the VVord finds out, and cuts off the firſt riſings and ſtirrings of it. The VVorld alwaies ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macked it, yet the VVord gets ground and is effectual, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, Come to a man in a Lethargy and pinch him, come to a man in a Phrenzy and tye him, <hi>Uterque iraſcitur, ſed uterque ſanatur;</hi> both are angry, but both are cured. But alas, how is this ſpiritual weapon neglected, undervalued, abuſed?</p>
                  <p>Some men know not the VVord, have no weapon in their houſes. They care not the Scriptures ſhould ſpeak any thing to them; Like that Cardinal <hi>Rivet</hi> mentions in his <hi>Orthodoxus Catholicus,</hi> who after he had heard <hi>Beza's</hi> Oration in the Poſſiack Convention, <hi>Utinam aut ille mutus fuiſſet, aut nos ſurdi eſſemus,</hi> I would either he had been dumb, or we deaf. <hi>Alcibiades</hi> hit a Schoolmaſter a box of the ear, becauſe he had not
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:62133:51"/> 
                     <hi>Homers</hi> VVorks in his School; how much more may we be angry with thoſe that have not the Bible in their houſes? Others undervalue the Scriptures, as <hi>Politian,</hi> that rejected them, as unfit for his poliſhed ſtile, and yet ſpent all his time upon trifles. <hi>Calderinus</hi> diſſwaded his Schollars from reading the Scriptures, yet Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented upon <hi>Virgils</hi> filthy Poeſie of <hi>Priapus.</hi> But take heed of deſpiſing the VVord. Take heed of bringing to it proud hearts. As ſome wear Swords to ſhew their gilded Pummels, and velvet Scabbards, ſo many uſe the VVord for oſtentation, rather than to ward off wicked ſuggeſtions with it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> As you ſhould obſerve Chriſt in the choice of his VVeapon, ſo make uſe of the skilfulneſs and aptneſs of Chriſt in the applying the VVord to the temptation, and in making uſe of the VVord againſt the variety of Satans temptations. You may obſerve how aptly, and readily Chriſt makes uſe of ſeveral Scriptures in reſiſting temptations, <hi>Mat. 4. 4. It is written man ſhall not live by bread alone,</hi> and therefore we ſhould depend upon the Providence of God in the midſt of ſtraights. <hi>It is written, thou ſhalt not tempt the Lord thy God,</hi> Ver. 7. and therefore we ſhould not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to expect bleſſings without the uſe of means, when God vouchſafes them to us. It is <hi>written, thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God,</hi> Ver. 10. therefore we muſt not blaſpheme him, and give his honour to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Now all theſe Scriptures our Saviour brings them out of one Book of God, they are all taken out of <hi>Deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teronomy.</hi> Now if one Book will afford ſuch plenty, what then will the whole Book of God? We ſhould therefore furniſh our ſelves with variety of Scriptures againſt variety of temptations. A Chriſtian that is well skilled in the Word is like one that hath a Plaiſter ready
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:62133:51"/> to lay on as ſoon as the wound is made, and thereby the danger is prevented. Therefore ſtudy the Scriptures, that you may have Antidotes againſt this and that tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, that you may have wherewith to anſwer Satan. <hi>Alſted</hi> (as I remember in his Caſes of Conſcience) tels of one <hi>Johannes Gatius</hi> that was ſo perfect in the Scriptures, that it was thought if all the Bible had been loſt, yet it might have been in a great meaſure recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by his dexterity and readineſs in it. It is a great commendation to be ready in the Scripture, but to be ſo ready as to improve it upon all occaſions againſt temptations is the glory and excellency of a Chriſtian. Get a skill in the Word, that you may have it in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs, and be able to apply it. It is true, knowledge is the eye of the ſoul, which muſt direct how it muſt be applied. Ignorant men pervert it to their own deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, they wound themſelves, not their enemies. But general diſcourſes are like the beams of the Sun diſperſed in the air, which warm and chear; but parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular application is like the beams collected in the burning glaſs, which unites the beams, and makes them burn. Apply the word to thy ſelf, if thou art tempted to Covetouſneſs, remember life conſiſts not in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance. If to uncleanneſs, the Lord knows how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the wicked, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 10. Eſpecially them that walk after the fleſh in the luſts of uncleanneſs, <hi>Heb. 13. 4. Whoremongers and Adulterers God will judge.</hi> If to inordinate fear, apply <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 4. If to diſtractions in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome times, that of <hi>Pſal. 55. 22. Caſt thy burden up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord.</hi> Thus have the Word in readineſs, like <hi>Solomons</hi> Worthies, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3. 8. that had their ſword on their thigh, ready to be out of the ſheath preſently, and labour for skill to manage it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Look to Chriſt as a pattern in his <hi>conſtancy</hi>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:62133:52"/> in reſiſting temptations; in his perſeverance againſt renewed aſſaults; our Saviour was long in the field, <hi>he was forty daies together tempted,</hi> Mar. 1. 13. Thoſe that are recorded in <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. were after the forty daies. When he had faſted forty daies, then the <hi>Tempter came,</hi> and perſwaded him to turn ſtones into bread; the Evangeliſts record only thoſe chief and laſt temptations. Now let us learn of our Captain to fight a good fight without diſcouragement, and without changes; though temptations change, yet let not us change, though they be multiplied, yet let us keep on our warfare and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain our courage.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Make uſe of Chriſt as a Pattern in the manner of reſiſting. Thus, by proportioning the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to the riſe and growth of temptations; when temptations riſe higher, and are more groſs, then we are to be more earneſt, proportioning our reſiſtance according to the vileneſs and ſinfulneſs of them. That temptation of Chriſt to blaſphemy, Chriſt did reject and reſiſt in another manner than he did the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. There he only anſwers, <hi>it is written,</hi> but here he ſaith, <hi>Get thee behind me Satan.</hi> He doth not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt it by the Word, but expreſſes a loathing and an indignation, and ſo ſhould we when temptations aſſault us, that ſtrike immediately at Gods glory, we ſhould expreſs a loathing, and abhorrency of them; and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, ſuch temptations to Atheiſm, Murder, Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are beſt reſiſted by abhorrency of them, and loathing them, not by diſputing with them, as <hi>Pariſienſis</hi> ſaith. Some temptations are reſiſted <hi>per fugam,</hi> by flight, as <hi>flee fornication.</hi> Some <hi>per indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem,</hi> by indignation, as a man hath his anger moved when he is offered nothing near the worth of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity. So when a man is tempted for trifles to ſin
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:62133:52"/> againſt God, and hazard his ſoul, <hi>Sola unius ſyllabae pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciatione ejus jacula confringuntur,</hi> &amp;c. It is enough to reſiſt ſuch temptations with that interjection, <hi>Fie, fie upon ſuch filthineſs, fie upon ſuch blaſphemy,</hi> and this is by many thought the ſafeſt way.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> You muſt make uſe of Chriſt as your aid and ſuccour, as well as your pattern; not only as a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern to know how to fight, but make uſe of his power and ſtrength to fight the better. <hi>Be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might,</hi> Eph. 6. 10. And Heb. 2. 18. <hi>He is ſaid to be able to ſuccour them that are tempted.</hi> Go not into the field therefore alone. In <hi>prophane Duels,</hi> wherein men challenge one another the field for ſmall punctillioes of honour, or happily for worſe things, (in which, as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Unus lethaliter peccat, alter aeternaliter perit,</hi> One mortally ſins, and the other eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally dies,) they ſeldom appear without <hi>Seconds,</hi> that they may ſee there be no wrong done, and that they may call for aid if need be. Much more ſhould Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in this divine Conflict, and wraſtling with Satan, take Chriſt along with them. We ſhould not go in the ſtrength of our own reſolutions, or our own vows, but we ſhould go againſt Satan, as <hi>David</hi> did againſt the Philiſtim, 1 <hi>Sam. 17. In the name of the Lord.</hi> VVhen we do ſo, we alwaies prevaile, and when we do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, we are alwaies foiled. No conflicting with Satan but in Gods ſtrength; remember Chriſt is able to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, he hath an ability of ſufficiency, and an ability that ariſes from experience.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p>THe foutrh Antidote <hi>is to be abundant in the uſe of prayer;</hi> as faith is the beſt of graces in reſiſting
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:62133:53"/> Satan, ſo prayer is the beſt of duties. The neglect of prayer was the beginning of <hi>Sauls</hi> fall, as moſt of the Fathers interpret that place, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. 19. VVhen <hi>Saul</hi> commanded the Prieſt to withdraw his hand from the Ark. They ſay of the Palm tree, that all its ſtrength lyeth on the top; it is true of a Chriſtian, all his ſtrength lies above. There is a threefold uſe of prayer. (1.) As a duty, for prayer is an offering, the Prophet compares it to Incenſe; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 141. A Sacrifice is but a viſible prayer, and prayer is nothing elſe but an audible Sacrifice. (2.) As a dignity, when a man doth abſtract himſelf from earth, and grow into a familiarity with God; it is a Mount <hi>Tabor,</hi> wherein the ſoul hath ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable transfigurations, and ſees not <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> but God. (3.) There is a neceſſity of prayer, for God hath left prayer as our City of refuge on all occaſions to flee to. <hi>Paul</hi> would have the <hi>Theſſal.</hi> pray, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, without ceaſing, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 17. The <hi>Epheſians</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 18. There is no duty at all times ſo ſeaſonable and uſeful as prayer. When we want bleſſings, prayer is the Key whereby we unlock the Treaſury of heaven, and gain the bleſſings we need. When we are aſſaulted by Satan, it is one of the beſt weapons we can uſe to defend our ſelves with. When <hi>David</hi> knew not how to withſtand the wiſdom of <hi>Achitophel,</hi> who was then as an Oracle of God, he praies, <hi>Lord turn the counſel of Achitophel unto fooliſhneſs, 2 Sam.</hi> 15. 31. So do thou pray, O Lord turn the counſel of this helliſh Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary into folly. So when <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> was in a great ſtrait, the Captains of the Enemy having beſet him about, 2 <hi>Chron. 18. 31. Jehoſhaphat cried out, and the Lord helped him, and moved them to depart from him.</hi> This now is our way to betake our ſelves to prayer, as <hi>Bernard</hi> excellently ſaith, <hi>Gravis quidem nobis tentati<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:62133:53"/> 
                     <hi>ſua, ſed longè gravior illioratio noſtra:</hi> His Temptations are grievous to us, but our Prayers are far more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to him. You do not know how you wound his head with Prayer, when he bruiſes your heel with Temptations. Therefore be much in prayer, it works deliverance from men, from devils, from all the ſtraits you can be ſurrounded with. <hi>For this cauſe,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor. 12. 8. I beſought the Lord thrice, viz.</hi> when he was under the buffetings of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. <hi>Pray,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>that you enter not into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> ſo pray that you fall not under temptation when you are entred. Prayer, it delivers <hi>out of temptation,</hi> Mat. 26. 41. <hi>Watch and pray that you enter not into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. In tentationem cadit, qui ad orationem non vadit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſologus,</hi> he is ſure to go into temptation that goes not to prayer. In temptation it gives a ſupply of ſtrength, <hi>Exod. 17. 11. Moſes</hi> Sword was ſtronger than <hi>Joſhuahs.</hi> And then it buckles on all our armour about us, for prayer is <hi>Armatura armaturae,</hi> the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of the Armour; and though it have no diſtinct part to which it is applied, yet it muſt be uſed with every piece of the Armour, without which all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour will be as no Armour.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. V.</head>
                  <p>THe fifth Antidote is, <hi>Take heed of giving place to the Devil.</hi> It is the Apoſtles counſel, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 27. That is, yield not the leaſt compliance with any tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation of Satan, <hi>Malae cogitationes ſunt antiqui ſerpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis caput,</hi> ſaith <hi>Jerom,</hi> The thought of evil is the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the head of the old Serpent, by which he will quickly wind in his whole body.</p>
                  <p>When you parly with Temptations, and take them
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:62133:54"/> by little and a little into your thoughts, which at the firſt riſing you ſhould ſpit at, the victory is half got by Satan. It is not good to let poyſon melt upon the tongue, it ſhould be preſently ſpit out. Daliances with temptations have proved fatal unto many, of which many inſtances might be given. It is a remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable ſaying of <hi>Solomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 10. 13. of a fooliſh man, <hi>the beginning of the words of his mouth is fooliſhneſs, but the end of his talk is miſchievous madneſs.</hi> If you admit the one, the other will follow.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VI.</head>
                  <p>THe ſixth Antidote is, <hi>Take heed of venturing upon the occaſions of ſin, and coming near the borders of temptation;</hi> do not expoſe your ſelves to them. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> in his 3 Sect. <hi>de fragmentis ſeptem miſericordiarum,</hi> ſaith of himſelf, <hi>Tribus modis memini, me ſervatum;</hi> That he was preſerved from ſin three waies: <hi>Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis ſubſtractione,</hi> by withdrawing the occaſion; <hi>Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendi datâ virtute,</hi> by having power given to reſiſt; <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionis ſanitate,</hi> by having his affections healed and changed. For I had, ſaith he, eaſily fallen into many ſins, <hi>Sed Deo miſerante,</hi> &amp;c. but God having mercy on me, did not ſuffer ſuch an occaſion to apprehend me. <hi>Job</hi> ſaith of himſelf, <hi>Chap. 31. 1. I have made a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with mine eyes, why then ſhould I think upon a maid?</hi> And <hi>Solomon</hi> bids thoſe that are given to wine, <hi>not to look upon it when it is red, when it giveth his colour in the cup, when it moveth it ſelf aright,</hi> Pro. 23. 31. Objects have in them a kind of efficiency, and they do work the heart accordingly to good or bad, as men are in themſelves good or bad. The beholding of Jeſus Chriſt, and the eying of him in his death and ſuffering, is an
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:62133:54"/> excellent and powerful means to mortifie luſts and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions. So to quicken any luſt, or corruption, is to preſent the object to the ſenſe, and the mind, which doth ſuddenly awaken thoſe corrupt diſpoſitions, and inclinations that are there, and call them out as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Iron doth that vertue that is in the Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone. Some Phyſicians ſay, that every body hath in it a natural Balſome, which will of it ſelf heal any wound or hurt the Creature hath received, provided it be kept clean from extrinſick putrefaction: But we are ſo far from this naturalBalſome, that we have in us a natural poyſon, that is, original ſin, that receives corroborati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as it were from every object and occaſion. Thus the Scripture tells us, that <hi>Eve</hi> her ſelf, when in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, <hi>ſaw the fruit that it was good,</hi> and was thereby induced to taſte of it, the bitterneſs whereof ſhe found unanſwerable to that what it promiſed to the ſight. Take heed therefore of coming near the borders of temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; beware of objects and occaſions that may enflame you; our hearts are powder, and therefore we muſt take heed of ſparks. Give not an indulgence, nor liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the eyes. <hi>Solomon</hi> when he played the Critick, <hi>he did not withhold his eyes from whatſoever he deſired, Eccl.</hi> 2. 10. But when you are to do the office of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, you muſt circumſcribe, and confine your eyes and other ſenſes. And if you would mortifie your eyes, mortifie your hearts; the eye and the heart have a great ſympathy. The way to keep your ſelves from being hurt by objects and occaſions, is to keep the heart pute, to ſubdue ſin there. Laying the Medicine to the heart, is like putting it to the wound: The other is like lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to the weapon, that is not ſo natural. We muſt therefore lay a ſtrict Law upon every member of our body, yet we muſt not think ſo to look to the heart, as
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:62133:55"/> to neglect the outward man. In Navigation, <hi>Coſmogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy</hi> is no leſs uſeful than <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> becauſe all the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations of the Stars, are in reference to the earth, and to the place to which they ſail: And in our ſpiritual Voyage to heaven, it is no leſs requiſite that we ſtudy the Map of our own earth, than to ſtudy the Globe of heaven whither we are ſailing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VII.</head>
                  <p>THe ſeventh Antidote againſt the Wiles of Satan, <hi>is diligence and induſtry in your calling.</hi> The Bird while it is flying is ſafe, but when it ſits and perches upon a tree, it becomes an object for any inſtruments where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to ſhoot it, and deſtroy it: And ſo a Chriſtian; when he is buſie in his Calling, is in a great meaſure ſafe from temptations, but when he becomes idle, and doth not buſie himſelf in that ſtation God hath ſet him in, he becomes fit ground and ſoyl for Satan to ſow any temptation and luſt in. Idleneſs expoſes the ſoul to all its ſpiritual enemies; and whereas it is the devils <hi>buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to tempt us, it is an idle mans buſineſs to tempt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</hi> It is a good anſwer to the devil when he tempts to ſin, <hi>Non licet,</hi> it is not lawful to do it: but it is a ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and better in ſomes opinion, <hi>Non vacat,</hi> I am not at leiſure. I cannot attend ſuch motions. Such anſwers do put Satan beyond his uſual arts, they put him more to a loſs. He had much rather enter a diſpute about the lawfulneſs, than be turned off with, <hi>I am not at leiſure.</hi> It is a golden rule Divines give to tempted perſons, to be diligent in their Callings; as I remember it was <hi>Jeroms</hi> advice to his friend <hi>Ruſticus, Semper boni operis aliquid, facito, ut diabolus ſemper te occupatum inveniat;</hi> To be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies doing ſome good, that the devil might alwaies
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:62133:55"/> find him imployed. Think of this, you who run out of your Callings, who neglect your Callings, who think it a piece of bondage to be ſubject to a Calling. Alas you are the nearer to temptation, and the more ſubject to be taken in his Wiles, <hi>Hoc habet ignavia, ut interdum ſecura ſit, tuta verò nunquam.</hi> This is the miſery of idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, an idle man is ſometimes ſecure, but never ſafe. <hi>Ille tutus, cui nullum imminet periculum, ſecurus qui non curat periculum.</hi> He is ſafe who is above danger, he is ſecure who fears no danger.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
                  <p>THe eighth Scripture Antidote, <hi>is ſincerity of heart;</hi> which many underſtand by the <hi>girdle of truth, Eph.</hi> 6. 14. Truth in its Latitude is by ſome underſtood in this place, but I ſhall propoſe it in a double conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: Firſt, Doctrinal, and ſo truth implies a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in our underſtandings to the will and mind of God. Truth in the general is nothing but the confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of one thing to another, whereof one is the Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pler, the other the Exemplification. The Sampler or Pattern is God, and the mind of God in his Word, and unto that ought every one to have their judgement and underſtanding ſo conformed, as to have it agreeing with it, and not to admit of other impreſſions, that are dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the Word of God. Thus in Scripture we are warned not to be <hi>toſſed to and fro with every wind of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> Eph. 4. 14. <hi>To hold fast the pattern of wholſome words,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 12. Secondly, Truth may be morally conſidered, as it is oppoſed to hypocriſie, and ſo it is the correſpondency of our outward actions to our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward affections, for as our inward affections muſt have their ſtamp from God, ſo muſt they endeavour to print
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:62133:56"/> their true ſtamp upon our actions, as the ſeed that is ſown in the ground, beareth the like ſeed above ground, and the fruit is not unlike the tree; no more ſhould we in our moralities, ſuſtain one perſon in our boſome, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in our countenance. This <hi>Aquinas</hi> calls ſimplicity, <hi>Subjicit virtuti veritatis ſimplicitatem, à quâ tantum ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, diſtinguitur, docetque illam nominari ſimplicitatem ex eo quid non tendat in diverſum,</hi> as <hi>Creſſolius</hi> obſerves, ſaith he, he refers ſimplicity to the topick of truth, from which it is only rationally diſtinguiſhed, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms us that it is called ſimplicity, becauſe it doth not tend to divers things, as inwardly to intend one thing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when outwardly it pretends another. This the Scripture holds forth, <hi>Joſh. 24. 14. Fear the Lord, and ſerve him in ſincerity, and in truth.</hi> Pſal. 51. 6. <hi>Thou loveſt truth in the inward man.</hi> Now both theſe branches as they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in this girdle of truth, ſo they are both neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to withſtand the Wiles of the Tempter. Get your judgements ſetled in the knowledge of the truth, ſo as not to be removed from it as the <hi>Galatians</hi> were, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 6. for it is the method of Satan, to hold forth falſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines in the ſimilitude of divine truths, by which he deceives the eyes of their judgements, who are unſtable in the waies of God. And here he begins in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is firſt corrupted, and then derives its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion to other faculties; as the bloud-ſhed eye is firſt vitiated, and then repreſents all objects of its own co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour; be ſure therefore to keep ſound your judgment. Oh into what an Abyſs of errour will corrupt principles in the underſtanding lead men into? But then labour alſo for ſincerity and uprightneſs of heart, which alone works conſtancy and perſeverance. Let there be no hypocriſie in your profeſſion of Religion. Labour to be <hi>Nathanaels</hi> and <hi>Jacobs.</hi> Get this in oppoſition to double minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:62133:56"/> diverſity of intereſts will make the mind unſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in all its actions. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>A double-minded man,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>James, is unſtable in all his waies,</hi> like a Wave of the Sea, toſſed to and fro. But when the heart is ſincere, and ſingle in the waies of God, when a man doth with a ſingle eye look at God, and his glory, he is greatly ſecured againſt Satan. Satan cannot do with him as he doth with another man. This girdle of truth is his ornament, and his ſtrength.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IX.</head>
                  <p>NInthly, I will lay down one general Rule, or Antidote, drawn from War; thoſe that write about Rules, and matters of War, give this as general counſel, as it is laid down by <hi>Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> de re mil. Lib. 3. c. 26. <hi>Quicquid tibi prodeſt adverſario no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet, quicquid illum juvat, tibi ſemper officit.</hi> Whatſoever is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to the Enemy, is hurtful to you, and whatſoever is profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to you, that is hurtful to your Enemy. For his gain is our loſs, his riſe our fall, his honour our ſhame, his help our hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. Therefore ſtudy with your ſelves what that is may advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage Satan in any kind, and be ſure that is hurtful for you: And if there be any thing profitable to you, that is hurtful to Satan. As Prayer, Heavenly Meditation, Converſe with Promiſes, Society with the Saints, all theſe, and many other of the like, muſt needs be good for us, becauſe they are detrimental to Satan.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. X.</head>
                  <p>TEnthly, and laſtly, <hi>As a powerful Antidote againſt Satans temptations, have an eye often to Scripture encouragements.</hi> The War into which a Chriſtian is entred, who wraſtles with the Prince and powers of darkneſs, is a fierce war, but yet you are not without encouragements in this War. If <hi>your enemy be great,</hi> God hath furniſhed you with good Armour, <hi>Put on then the whole Armour of God,</hi> Eph. 6. 13. it is called Gods Armour, becauſe it is made by God. The Hebrew uſes to put the name of God to things, to note the excellency of them. No Weapons will ſerve to fight
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:62133:57"/> againſt the devil but Gods, nothing will make you ſhot-free but the Armour of God. Now, as your encouragement is in having this Armour, ſo your ſafety lies in putting on the whole Armour; it hath all the ſame Maker, it is all the ſame Mettal, not like <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzars</hi> Image, the head Gold, the breaſt Silver; all is alike precious, and all alike uſeful. Now therefore <hi>put on</hi> your Armour. If your <hi>Enemy be ſubtil,</hi> you have an expert Captain. <hi>If the brunt and conflict</hi> be hard, look often to <hi>the Crown that is promiſed, Jam.</hi> 1. 12. Will not a Crown make a full recompence? <hi>Si victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſi fuerimus hic illic erimus glorioſi,</hi> as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith. If here we are victorious, there we ſhall be glorious, having inſtead of a Helmet a Diadem, for a Sword a Palm, for a Shield, <hi>Chlamidem deauratam,</hi> a Cloak or Mantle wrought with Gold; for the Breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate the Robe of delight. And is it not in the mean time better, <hi>Premi, quam perimi,</hi> to be kept low, than utterly ruined? Is it not better to bear the weight of our Armour, than feel the fiery darts of the malignant one? If you dread becauſe Satan <hi>is a fiery Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent:</hi> Remember Jeſus Chriſt is that <hi>Brazen Serpent</hi> who can heal all his ſtings. If you are afraid of his roaring becauſe he is a Lion, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>a devouring Lion, and a roaring Lion:</hi> Remember Jeſus Chriſt is the <hi>Lion of the Tribe of Judah;</hi> he is a Lion for valour, as the other is for cruelty. You have then three great encouragements, your <hi>Captain is ſtronger, your Armour better,</hi> and <hi>your Reward excellent, and glorious.</hi> And therefore when you think the preſſure is hard, and the fight bloudy, remember theſe are the things which uſe to encourage other Souldiers, and ſhould much more encourage Chriſtian Souldiers.</p>
                  <p>And now do not lay up theſe Antidotes in a paper, as you uſe to do Antidotes that are preſcribed by a Phyſician, that you will uſe when you pleaſe, but uſe theſe continually, have them about you in a readineſs. Satan is alwaies tempting, he hath alwaies fiery darts about him, though he doth not throw them. He is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies biting at the heel, therefore be you alwaies ready to make reſiſtance. And do not think theſe things are uſeful in times of great trial, but not <hi>now.</hi> This is a Wile of Satan to keep you from profiting, and therefore look on what hath been ſaid, as a Call from heaven to awaken you to diligence in your Chriſtian War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, and to reſiſt him who hath many devices to deſtroy you, and who abounds in all ſubtilty and induſtry to bring his devices to paſs.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:62133:57"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
